<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fides divina: the ground of true faith asserted. Or, A useful and brief discourse, shewing the insufficiency of humane, and the necessity of divine evidence for divine or saving faith and Christian religion to be built upon. Being a transcript out of several authors extant.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1598_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867789</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96982)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 202:E1598[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fides divina: the ground of true faith asserted. Or, A useful and brief discourse, shewing the insufficiency of humane, and the necessity of divine evidence for divine or saving faith and Christian religion to be built upon. Being a transcript out of several authors extant.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 107, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fides Divina:</hi> The Ground of TRUE FAITH Aſſerted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A uſeful and brief Diſcourſe, ſhewing the inſufficiency of humane, and the neceſſity of Divine Evidence for divine or ſaving Faith and Chriſtian Religion to be built upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being a Tranſcript out of ſeveral Authors extant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 10.37.</hi>
               </bibl> If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 15.24.</hi>
               </bibl> If I had not done among them the works that none other man did, they had not had ſin; but now have they both ſeen and hated both me and my Father.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 2.4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl> My ſpeech and my preaching was not with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſible words of mans wiſdom, but in demonſtration of the Spirit and of Power, That your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:170139:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170139:2"/>
            <p>A Juſt and neceſſary Vindication of all ſuch as endeavour to be ſatisfied concerning the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentickneſs and demonſtrative authority and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Copies, or Tranſlations of Scripture, or any Expoſitions, Doctrines, or Concluſions drawn from them to be a ground ſufficient for Divine and ſaving Faith; ſcruples herein unavoidably ariſing from the Tongues and Pens even of the learned themſelves, who both in publike and private will of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en tell us, That this or that is not rightly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, but ſhould be read out of the Hebrew or Greek word for word, thus, or thus much different from the Tranſlation; or that this, or that word or ſentence is not in ſome, or moſt of their Greek Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, or here or there ſhould be a Parentheſis; or that the Comma is not rightly placed, or the like; ſomething or other is uſually amiſs, eſpecially when from ſome Text of Scripture the unreaſonable or doubtfulneſs of their Opinions or Doctrines are queſtioned.</p>
            <p>In further proſecution hereof, I ſhall not need to cite any of the learned Papiſts, who urge many ſhrewd Arguments and Reaſons to prove the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our Scriptures, and the inſufficiency of any Scripture for the purpoſes aforementioned. Nor need I inſiſt on our learned Countreyman, Mr. <hi>Hugh Broughton,</hi> though a Proteſtant, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great Linguiſt, charged the Biſhops with perverting the Text in the Old Teſtament in the Engliſh Tranſlations, in <hi>848.</hi> places. Nor on the Charge delivered to King <hi>JAMES</hi> by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Lincoln Dioceſs;</hi> telling him in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170139:3"/>of their grievances, That the Engliſh Tranſlation of the Bible was ſuch, as takes away from the Text, and addes to the Text, and that to the changing or obſcuring of the meaning of the Holy Ghost. Nor yet on the palpable differences and contradictions in Tranſlations, wherein ſome Texts are rendred with much ſuſpition of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, untruth, or both, obſerved by private men.</p>
            <p>Nor will I at preſent deſcant, Whether it was through negligence, ignorance, or deſign in the Tranſlators or otherwiſe, that all this was done; yet that <hi>de facto,</hi> it is ſo done, may be ſeen, and muſt be confeſt by all intelligent men, not blinded with ſuperstition like the Epheſians, <hi>Acts 19.17, 18.</hi> nor pindiced with worldly intereſt, like the chief Rulers, <hi>Joh. 12.42, 43.</hi> But for the preſent (among many other that might be cited) I ſhall produce ſome few modern Engliſh Proteſtant Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of moſt eminent learning whoſe concurrent Teſtimony herein (together with the precedent and ſubſequent conſiderations) may be more then ſufficient to our purpoſe, it being alſo back't with ſuch Arguments and Reaſons as are evident to our own understanding and experience.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170139:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe Tranſlators of King JAMES his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their Epiſtle to the Reader, do ſet forth how they wtre charged and upbraided by ſome of their Brethren, as well as by the Papiſt, in that they ſo often altered and changed the Bible by their new tranſlating it thus, <q>
                  <hi>viz. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens mouths have been open</hi> a good while (and yet are not ſtopped) vvith ſpeeches about the tranſlation ſo long in hand, or rather peruſals of Tranſlations made before, and ask vvhat may be the reaſon, vvhat the neceſſity of the Employment; hath the Church been deceived, ſay they, all this vvhile? Hath her ſvveet bread been mingled vvith leaven, her ſilver vvith droſs, her Wine vvith Water, her Milk vvith Lime, (<hi>Lactè Gypſum malè inceſtur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>) We hoped that vve had been in the right vvay, that vve had had the Oracles of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto us, and that though all the vvorld had cauſe to be offended, and to complain, yet vve had none. Hath the Nurſe holden out the Breaſt, and nothing but vvind in it? Hath the bread been delivered by the Fathers of the Church, and the ſame proved to be <hi>Lapidoſus,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh? What is to handle the Word of God deceitfully, if this be not? Thus certain Brethren. Alſo the Adverſaries of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> like <hi>Samballat</hi> in <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> mock, as vve hear, both at the vvork and vvorkmen, ſaying, What do theſe vveak <hi>Jews, &amp;c?</hi> Will they make the ſtones vvhole again out of the heaps of duſt vvhich are burnt? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they build, yet if a Fox go up, he ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170139:4"/>even break dovvn their ſtony Wall; Was their Tranſlation good before? Why do they novv mend it? Was it not good? Why then vvas it obtruded to the people? Yea, VVhy did the Catholicks (meaning Popiſh Romaniſts) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes go in Jeopardy for refuſing to go to hear it? Nay, if it muſt be tranſlated into Engliſh, Catholicks are fitteſt to do it; They have learning, and they knovv vvhen a thing is vvell; they can <hi>manum de tabula:</hi> VVe vvill anſvver them both briefly; The former being Brethren, thus <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And after their anſvvering theſe, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver the Papiſts and retort as many or more faults of the ſame kind, upon them in theſe vvords follovving, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>Yet before vve end vve muſt anſvver a cavil and objection of theirs againſt us, for altering and amending our Tranſlations ſo oft, vvherein they deal hardly and ſtrangely vvith us, for to vvhom ever vvas it imputed for a fault (by ſuch as vvere vviſe) to go over that vvhich he had done, and to amend it vvhere he ſavv cauſe? Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vvas not afraid to exhort St. <hi>Hierome</hi> to a <hi>Palmodia,</hi> or Recantation. The ſame St. <hi>Augustine</hi> vvas not aſhamed to retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, vve might ſay revoke, many things that had paſſed him, and doth even glory that he ſeeth his infirmities: If vve vvill be ſons of the Truth, vve muſt conſider vvhat it ſpeaketh, and trample upon our ovvn credit, yea, and upon other mens too, if either be any vvay an hinderance to it. This to the cauſe: Then to the perſons vve ſay, That of all men they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170139:4"/>ought to be moſt ſilent in this caſe; for what va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety have they, &amp; what alterations have they made, not only of their Service-Books Porteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Breviaries, but alſo of their <hi>Latine</hi> Tranſlation: The Service-Book ſuppoſed to be made by St. <hi>Ambroſe (Officium Ambroſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi>) was a great while in ſpecial uſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; but Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> called a Councel, with the aid of <hi>Charls</hi> the Emperor, aboliſhed it, yea burnt it and commanded the Service-Book of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> univerſally to be uſed: Well, <hi>Officium Gregorianum</hi> gets by this means to be in credit; but doth it continue without change or altering? No; the very <hi>Romen</hi> Service was of two Faſhions, the new Faſhion, and the old (the one uſed in one Church, the other in another) as is to be ſeen in <hi>Pamilius,</hi> a <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist,</hi> his preface before <hi>Micrologus:</hi> The ſame <hi>Pamilius</hi> reporteth out of <hi>Radalphus de Rive,</hi> That about the year of our Lord, 1277 Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third removed out of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Rome</hi> the more ancient Books (of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) and brought into uſe the Miſſals of the Fryars <hi>Minorites,</hi> and commanded them to be obſerved there; inſomuch, that about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeers after, when the above named <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphus</hi> happened to be at <hi>Rome,</hi> he found all the Books to be new (after the new ſtamp) Neither was this chopping &amp; changing in the ancient times only, but alſo of late, <hi>Pius Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> himſelf confeſſeth, That every Biſhopprick almoſt, had a peculiar kind of Service, moſt unlike to that which others had, which moved him to aboliſh all other Breviaries, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170139:5"/>ſo ancient, and priviledged, and publiſhed by Biſhops in their Dioceſſes, and to eſtabliſh and ratifie that only which was of his own ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth, in the year 1568. Now when the Father of their Church, who gladly would heal the ſore of the Daughter of his people ſoftly and ſlightly, and make the beſt of it, finding ſo great fault with them for their odds and jarring, we hope the children have no great cauſe to vaunt of their uniformity. But the difference that appeareth in our Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and our often correcting of them, is the thing that we are ſpecially charged with: Let us ſee therefore, whether they themſelves be without fault this way (if it be to be counted a fault to correct) or whether they be fit men to throw ſtones at us; <hi>o tandem major pareas minori;</hi> they that are leſs ſound themſelves, ought not to object infirmities to others. If we ſhould tell them that <hi>Valla, Stapulenſis, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſinus,</hi> and <hi>Vives,</hi> found fault with their vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Tranſlation, and conſequently, wiſhed the ſame to be mended, or a new one to be made; they would anſwer peradventure, That we produced their Enemies for Witneſſes againſt them; albeit, they were in no other ſort Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies then St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> for telling them the truth; and it were to be wiſhed that they had dared to tell it them plainer &amp; oftner. But what will they ſay to this, That <hi>Pope Leo</hi> the tenth allowed <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Tranſlation of the New Teſtament, ſo much different from the vulgar, by his Apoſtolick Letter and Bull, That the ſame <hi>Leo</hi> exhorted Pagnine to tranſlate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170139:5"/>the whole Bible, and bare whatſoever charges was neceſſary for the Work; ſurely, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reaſoneth to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that if the former Law and Teſtament had been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, there had been no need of the later: So we may ſay, That if the old Vulgar had been at all points ollowable, to ſmall purpoſe had labour and charges been undergone about framing a new: If they ſay it was one Popes private Opinion, and that he conſulted onely himſelf; then we are able to go further with them, and to aver, That more of their chief men of all ſorts, even their own Trent-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, <hi>Paiva &amp; Vega;</hi> and their own Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>Hierominus ab Oleaſtro;</hi> and their own Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Iſadorus Clarius,</hi> and their own Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Thomas a vio Caietan,</hi> do either make new Tranſlations themſelves, or follow new ones of other mens making, or note the Vulgar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter for halting; none of them fear to diſſent from him, nor yet to except againſt him: And call they this an uniform Tenor of Text, &amp; judgement about the Text, ſo many of their Worthies diſclaiming the now received conceit? Nay, we will yet come a little nearer the quick; doth not their <hi>Paris</hi> Edition differ from the <hi>Lovaine</hi> and <hi>Hentenius</hi> his from them both, and yet all of them allowed by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Nay, doth not <hi>Sextus Quintus</hi> confeſs, That certain Catholicks (he meaneth certain of his own ſide) were in ſuch a humour of tranſlating the Scriptures into <hi>Latine,</hi> that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan taking occaſion by them, though they thought of no ſuch matter, did ſtrive what
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170139:6"/>he could, out of ſuch uncertain and manifold a variety of Tranſlations, ſo to mingle all things that nothing might ſeem to be left cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and firm in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay further, did not the ſame <hi>Sextus</hi> ordain by an inviolable Decree, and that with the counſel and conſent of the Cardinals, That the Latine Edition of the Old and New Teſtament, which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Trent</hi> would have to be authentick, is the ſame without controverſie which he then ſet forth, being diligently Corrected and Printed in the Printing Houſe of the <hi>Vatican;</hi> thus <hi>Sextus</hi> in his Preface before his Bible. And yet <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, his immediate Succeſſor (to account of) publiſheth another Edition of the Bible, containing in it infinite differences from that of <hi>Sextus</hi> (and many of them weighty and material) and yet this muſt be authentick by all means. What is it to have the faith of our glorious Lord Jeſus Chriſt with yea and nay, if this be not? Again, what is ſweet harmony and conſent if this be? Therefore as <hi>Dimaratus</hi> of <hi>Corinth</hi> adviſed a great King before he talked of the diſſentions among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> to compoſe his own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick broils; ſo all the while that our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do make ſo many and ſo various Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons themſelves, and do jarre ſo much about the worth and authority of them, they can with no ſhew of Equity challenge us for chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and correcting: Thus far the ſaid Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</q> From which may be obſerved, At what great uncertainty the moſt wiſe and learned on both ſides have been, and are about the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170139:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>conteſting which ſide hath the true, not knowing that either ſide hath it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At what great uncertainty they likewiſe are in reſpect of thoſe Scriptures which they have, not certainly knowing the undoubted true ſenſe and meaning thereof; this plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that they do on each ſide ſo often alter, change, amend, and new tranſlate their reſpective Bibles, wherein will be found many variations, if not contradictions to the former; and when they have done all they can, it will be far from ſatisfying all the learned of the ſame party, who having opportunity; will alter and new tranſlate it to their own minds, which will as much diſpleaſe others, who will take their turn again to alter it; and in this manner may it run <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> from time to time, and ſtill upon like uncertainties and that the caſe is no better with us, our next Author more fully ſets forth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi> Dr. in Divinity, and a great Schollar, he in his Diſcourſe of Liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying pag. 61, 62, 63. ſhews, and by many Reaſons proves that which in effect amounts to an impoſſibility for any man to find out a true Copy or Tranſlation, or right ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; his words are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz.</hi> 
               <q>There are ſo many thouſand of Copies that are writ by perſons of ſeveral intereſts and perſwaſions, ſuch different underſtandings and tempers, ſuch diſtinct abilities and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that it is no wonder there is ſo great variety of readings both in the Old and New Teſtament. In the old Teſtament the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170139:7"/>Jews pretend that the Chriſtians have corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many places, on purpoſe to make ſymphony between both the Teſtaments: On the other ſide the Chriſtians have had ſo much reaſon to ſuſpect the Jews, That when <hi>Aquilla</hi> had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the Bible in their Schools, and had been taught by them they rejected the Edition, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, and ſome of them called it Hereſie to follow it. And <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> juſtified to <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> That the Jews had defalk'd many ſayings from the Books of the Old Prophets, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt he inſtances that of the Pſalm, <hi>Dicite in Nationibus quia Dominus Regnavit à ligno.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Engliſhed: Tell it (or ſay, <hi>i.e.</hi>) amongſt the Nations, the Lord hath raigned for (or by) the wood or tree.</p>
               <p>The laſt words they have cut off, and prevailed ſo far in it, that to this day none of our Bibles have it; but if they ought not to have it, then <hi>Juſtin Martyr's</hi> Bible had more in it then it ſhould have, for there it was; ſo that a fault there was eitheir under or over: But however, there are infinite readings of the New Teſtament (for in that I will inſtance) ſome whole verſes in one that are not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and there was in ſome Copies of Saint <hi>Marks</hi> Goſpel, in the laſt chapter a whole verſe, a chapter it was anciently called, that is not found in our Bibles, as St. <hi>Hierom ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibiam Q.</hi> 3. notes; the words he repeats <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Contra Polygamos: Et illi ſatis faciebant dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170139:7"/>ſaeculum istu &amp; iniquitatis &amp; incredulitatis ſubſtantia eſt, quae non ſivit per immundos ſpiritus veram Dei apprehendi vertutem, idcirto jam nunc revela juſtitiam tuam.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Engliſhed. And they did ſatisfie, ſaying, that age is the ſubſtance of iniquity and incredulity, which by reaſon of unclean ſpirits, doth not ſuffer the virtue, power, or efficacie of God to be apprehended; therefore now reveal thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Theſe words are thought by ſome to ſavour of <hi>Manichaiſm,</hi> and for ought I can find, were therefore rejected out of many <hi>Greek</hi> Copies, and at laſt out of the <hi>Latine, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Parable of the woman taken in Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is now in <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſayes, It was not in any Goſpel, but the Goſpel <hi>ſecundum Hebraeos;</hi> and St. <hi>Hierome</hi> makes it doubtful, and ſo doth St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Euthimius,</hi> the firſt not vouchſafing to explicate it in <hi>Homolies</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>John,</hi> the other affirming it not to be found in the exacter Copies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But the inſtances in this kinde are too many, as appears in the variety of readings in ſeveral Copies, proceeding from the negligence or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators, or the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Graci corruperunt novum Teſtamentum ut Teſtantur:</hi> Tertul. l. 5. ado. Marcion. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. L. 5. Hiſt. C. ult. Irenae: l. 1. c. 29. Allu. Haereſ. Bafil. L. 2. Contr. Eunomium</note> endeavour of Hereticks, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting Marginal Notes into the Text, or the neerneſs of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in pag. 82. he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170139:8"/>ſaith, <q>That ſince there are in Scripture many myſteries and matters of queſtion, upon which there is a vail; ſince there are ſo many Copies, with infinite variety of readings; ſince a vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous interpunction, a Parentheſis, a Letter, an Accent, may much alter the ſenſe; ſince ſome places have divers litteral ſenſes, many have ſpiritual, myſtical, and allegorical meanings; ſince there are ſo many trops, metononies, ironies, hyperbolies, properties and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Languages, whoſe underſtanding depends upon ſuch circumſtances, that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to know its proper interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; now that the proper knowledge of ſuch circumſtances and particular ſtories is irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably loſt; ſince there are ſome myſteries which at the beſt advantage of expreſſion are not eaſily to be apprehended, and whoſe explication, by reaſon of our imperfections, muſt needs be dark, ſometimes weak, ſometimes untelligable: And laſtly, Since thoſe ordinary means of expounding Scripture, as ſearching the Originals, conference of places, purity of reaſon, analogie of faith, are all dubious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and very fallible; he that is wiſeſt, and by conſequence the likelieſt to expound trueſt, in all probability of reaſon will be very far from confidence, becauſe every one of theſe, and many more, are like ſo many degrees of improbabilities and incertainty, all depreſſing our certtainty of finding out the truth in ſuch myſteries, and amidſt ſo many difficulties; and therefore a wiſe man that conſiders this would not willingly be preſcribed to by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170139:8"/>and therefore if he be alſo a juſt man, he will not impoſe it upon others; for it is beſt every man ſhould be left to that Liberty from which no man can juſtly take him, unleſs he could ſecure him from Error.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in pag. 82. he tells us, <q>That <hi>Oſiander</hi> in his confutation of a Book which <hi>Melanchthon</hi> wrote againſt him, obſerves, That there are twenty ſeveral Opinions concerning Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all drawn from Scriptures by the men onely of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Confeſſion; there are ſixteen ſeveral Opinions conncerning Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin; and as many definitions of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as there are Sects of men that diſagree about them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And then he propoſeth a queſtion with i'ts anſwer, in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And now what help is there for us in the midſt of theſe uncertainties? if we follow any one Tranſlation, or any one mans Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, what Rule have we to chooſe the right by? Or is there any one man that hath tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated perfectly, or expounded infallibly? No Tranſlation challenges ſuch a prerogative as to be authentick, but the vulgar Latine, and yet ſee with what ſucceſs; for when it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared authentick by the Councel of <hi>Trent, Sextus</hi> put forth a Copy much amended of what it was, and tyed all men to follow that; but that did not ſatisfie; for Pope <hi>Clement</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views and corrects it in many places, and ſtill the Decree remains in a changed ſubject. And ſecondly, that Tranſlation will be very unapt to ſatisfie, in which one of their own <hi>Iſſidore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170139:9"/>Clarius</hi> a Monk of <hi>Breſtia</hi> found and amended 8000. faults; beſides innumerable others, which he ſayes he pretermitted. And then thirdly, To ſhew how little themſelves were ſatisfyed with it, divers learned men among them did new tranſlate the Bible, and thought they did God and the Church good ſervice in it. So that if you take this for your preſident, you are ſure to be miſtaken infinittly; if you take any other, the Authors themſelves do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you any ſecurity: If you reſolve to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any one as far only as you ſee cauſe, then you only do wrong or right by chance, for you have certainty juſt proportionable to your own skill, to your own infallibility. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to folllow any one whitherſoever he leads, we ſhall oftentimes come thither where we ſhall ſee our ſelves to become ridiculous.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far that learned and ingenuous Doctor who alſo ſhews, and by many pregnant inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and reaſons proves the reſults of Councels, Fathers, Traditions, yea, of Churches, Popes and pretenders to have the Spirit, to be all dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, very fallible, and uncertain, yea often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to themſelves, and to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore from all or any of theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in reſpect of the former uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties cannot be expected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Joh. Goodwin,</hi> a man both of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and deep judgement, who though he hath already diſcovered much more herein then any of our diſſenting Brethren would hitherto ever acquaint us with, yet it is ſuppoſed to be much
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170139:9"/>leſſe then he knows, (which for his own accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation and ſecurity, its thought by ſome) he conceals not ſo much from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, as from the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> of the ſame ſpirit, though under ſeveral more ſpecious forms of godlineſs, but are much worſe, and more to be abhorred then the other, by how much we appear more like Angels of Light, yet act from the very ſame Principle of ſelf-intereſt upon pretence of Divine Right and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as unjuſtly challenged and uſurped by any of theſe, as by the other, or by any formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and removed for the like uſurpation and practiſe, whereby they would ſubject other mens judgements and conſciences to their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates (even as the other do) and bow them as it were to dead Images, ſet up only in ſome finer ſhapes and dreſſes meerly of their own divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and upon refuſal, to judge them Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Hereticks, expoſing them thereby to the hatred, rage and contempt of the people, who (being generally led by ſtupid ignorance, ſuperſtitious zeal, and blind devotion) are (in all ſuch caſes) outragious, like the waves of the ſea, hurried to and again, even as the wind and the tide of Authority and Doctrine drives them; and not ceaſing here, they will diſpoſe them to utter deſtruction, at leaſt, to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, whereto they can get the Civil Powers concurrence; or, as in more plain Engliſh it s ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. As the Kings of the earth ſhall give their power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt, wherein they deal moſt injuriouſly and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely in depriving men of that natural native
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170139:10"/>Right which God hath given to every man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born a rational creature, to be ſaved by his own Faith, and therefore muſt have that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in matters of Religion and Worſhip, as to be led by the reſult of his own underſtanding, and not of any other mans.</p>
            <p>Yet all this brutiſh wickedneſs among the ſons of men, is no more then what St. <hi>John</hi> long ſince foreſaw would come to paſs, namely, That the Kings of the earth ſhould not only give their power and ſtrength to the Beaſt, and commit fornication with the Whore, but alſo, that the Inhabitants of the Earth ſhould be made drunk with the Wine of her Fornication, even with the blood of the Saints; and that power ſhould be given to the Beaſt, not only to cauſe it ſelf to be worſhipped, but to make war with the Saints, and to overcome them: All which being thus foretold, what marvel then is it to ſee the generality of men ſo drunk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as to thirſt for the deſtruction of their harmleſs Neighbors and friends, more then to ſee a common Drunkard in his drunken frenzie to ſtob or kill his own Brother or Friend, whom he ought (and out of that drunken fit would) moſt dearly love and reſpect; but it is a great rarity and wonder (almoſt like the ſight of a black Swan) to ſee any in a high place and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo far recovered out of this zealous ſpiritual drunkenneſs, as to know, and openly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the aforeſaid <hi>natural Right</hi> to be a <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,</hi> and every mans due, and <hi>that he that would have it ought to give it,</hi> conſtituting a Law for every mans enjoying it accordingly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170139:10"/>it is no ſuch wonder to ſee ſuch ſo far to relapſe again into that Epedemical diſtemper, as by ſome forraign ſenſe put upon that Law; or by ſome hidden &amp; reſerved intention of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers (unintelligable by any words therein) in effect quite to uull and make void the ſame, making it a meer empty ſhell without the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; a meer Character without any certain ſenſe or meaning; or a meer ſnare to men for their deſtruction, rather then any ſecurity for their preſervation; for if there had been no ſuch Law, and inſtead thereof ſome poſitive Law made to the contrary; might not they then as well by ſuch a reſerved ſenſe and intention have preſerved whom they had pleaſed? and is it any otherwiſe by having a Law for ſecurity, when by ſuch a reſerved ſenſe or intention they may ſuffer whom they pleaſe to be deſtroyed? Where's then the difference? My dulneſs is ſuch (I muſt confeſs) that I can ſee little, or none at all.</p>
            <p>And if it be no better from the beſt of men, what can be expected from the worſt (whereof the generality conſiſts) who with open mouth cry for fire from heaven (when otherwiſe they cannot procure it) to devour all men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Judgements to their own, quite forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of what ſpirit they are, and not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering from whence that inhumane and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat proceeds; but the unreaſonableneſſe of theſe is well ſet forth by a learned and ingenuous Author, in theſe words following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170139:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>It is unnatural and unreaſonable to perſecute diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing Opinions; unnatural, for underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing wholly ſpiritual, cannot be reſtrained, and therefore neither puniſhed by corporal afflictions; It is alienà republica, a matter of another world; you may as well cure the Collick by bruſhing a mans clothes, or fill a mans belly with a ſyllogiſm; theſe things do not communicate in matter, and therefore neither in action nor paſſion; and ſince all puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a prudent Government puniſh the offendor to prevent a future crime, and ſo it proves more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal then vindiclive, the punitive act being in order to the cure and prevention; and ſince no pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment of the body can cure a diſeaſe in the ſoul, it is diſproportionable in nature and in all civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to puniſh where the puniſhment can do no good; it may be an act of Tyranny, but never of Juſtice; for is an Opinion ever the more true or falſe, for being perſecuted, ſome men have believed it the more, as being provoked into a confidence, and vexed into a reſolution; but the thing it ſelf is not the truer; and though the Hang-man may confute a man with an inexplicable delemma, yet not convince his underſtanding; for ſuch premiſes can infer no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion but that of a mans life and a wolfe way as well give Laws to the underſtanding, as he whoſe diſtates are only propounded in violence, and writ in blood; and a dog is as capable of Law as a man, if there be no choice in his obedience, nor diſcourſe in his choice, nor reaſon to ſatisfie his diſcourſe. And as it is unnatural, ſo it is unreaſonable, that</hi> Sempro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius <hi>ſhould force</hi> Caius <hi>to be of his Opinion, becauſe</hi> Sempronius <hi>is Conſul this year and commands the Lictors; as if he that can kill a man cannot but be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170139:11"/>infallible; and if he be not, why ſhould I do violence to my conſcience, becauſe he can do violence to my perſon. Force in matters of Opinion can do no good, but is very apt to do hurt, for no man can change his Opinion when he will, or be ſatisfied in his reaſon that his Opinion is falſe becauſe diſcountenanced; if a man could change his opinion when he liſts, he might cure many inconveniences of his life; all his fears and his ſorrows would ſoon disband if he would but alter his Opinion, whereby he is perſwaded that ſuch an accident that afflicts him is an evil, and ſuch an object formidable, let him but believe himſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable, or that he receives a benefit when he is plundered, diſgraced, impriſoned, condemned and afflicted, neither his ſleeps need to be disturbed nor his quietneſs diſcompoſed; but if a man cannot change his Opinion when he liſt, nor ever doth hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily or reſolutely; but when he cannot do otherwiſe, then to uſe force may make him an hypocrite, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be a right believer; and ſo inſtead of erecting a Trophee for God and true Religion, to build a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument for the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Infinite examples are recorded in Church ſtory to this very purpoſe, but <hi>Socrates</hi> inſtances in one for all; for when <hi>Elucius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zicum,</hi> was threatned by the Emperor <hi>Valence</hi> with baniſhment and confiſcation if he did not ſubſcribe to the Decree of <hi>Ariminum;</hi> at laſt he yeelded to the <hi>Arian</hi> Opinion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fell into great torment of conſcience o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly at <hi>Cyzicum,</hi> recanted the Error, asked God and the Church forgiveneſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the Emperors injuſtice, and that was all the good the <hi>Arian</hi> party got by offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170139:12"/>violence to his conſcience; and ſo many families in <hi>Spain,</hi> which are (as they call them) new Chriſtians, and of a ſuſpected Faith, into which they were forced by the Tyranny of the Inquiſition, and yet are ſecret <hi>Moors,</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough of the inconvenience of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a Doctrine more gladly <hi>Ceventandi;</hi> for it either puniſhes a man for keeping a good conſcience, or forces him into a bad; it either puniſhes ſincerity, or perſwades hypocriſie; it perſecutes a truth, or drives into an error; and it teaches a man to diſſemble, and to be ſafe, but never to be honeſt.</q> Thus far he.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all which, where can we ſee it otherwiſe with any Nation or people in any form of religious Worſhip, but that they have drank ſo deep of that Whores cup, as to thirſt for the blood of their oppoſites, eſpecially if they ſhall but in the leaſt diſcover to the world the unſoundneſs of the foundation on which their <hi>Babel</hi> is built.</p>
            <p>All which the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>G.</hi> well knowing, and by experience finding, that a little Light will much offend the tender ſights of many, who therefore (like Owls in the dark) will both skreech and ſtrick at the meer ſhine of a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; yet nevertheleſs in this <hi>Divine Authority of Scripture,</hi> pag 10. he tells us, <hi>If no Tranſlation whatſoever, nor any any, either written or printed Copy whatſoever be the Word of God, or foundation of Religion, certainly our Engliſh Tranſlations can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not challenge this honor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170139:12"/>
            <p>And in pag. 18. of the ſame (he ſaith) <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs no writing whatſoever, whether Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Originals, are the foundation of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in his <hi>Youngling Elder,</hi> pag. 35. (he ſaith) <hi>It is very poſſible, that either through negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ignorance, want of memory, or the like in Scribes and Correctors of the Preſs, ſome ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror may be found in every Copy of the Scriptures now extant in the world, which will render this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py contradictious to it ſelf; yea, it is poſſible that many ſuch errors as this may be found in the beſt and trueſt Copies that are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 36. page of the ſame Book (he ſaith) <q>The true and proper foundation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is intrinſecally, eſſentially, and in the nature of it unchangeable, unalterable in the leaſt by the wills, pleaſures, or attempts of men. But there is no Book, or Books what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, Bible, or other, but in the contents of them may be altered or changed by men.</q> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> The major he proveth thus; <q>If the proper Foundation of Religion were intrinſecally, and in the nature of it changeable and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by men,</q> then can it not be any matter of truth, becauſe the nature of truth is like the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God himſelf, unchangeable, unalterable <q>by men, Angels Devils, or any creature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; yea God himſelf cannot alter it any whit, more then deny himſelf, or change his own nature or being,</q>
            </p>
            <p>And for the minor (ſaith he) <q>That alſo is no leſs evident, experience teacheth us, that Books or Bibles themſelves are <hi>de facto,</hi> changed and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170139:13"/>altered by men from time to time, every new Edition or Impreſſion, almoſt, commending it ſelf, for ſomewhat corrected or amended in it, which was delinquent or defective in the former.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this learned Author (notwithſtanding all the aforeſaid paſſages of his) in his <hi>Divine Authority of Scripture,</hi> pag. 13. doth affirm, <q>If by Scripture be meant the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things contained and held forth in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, commonly known amongſt Proteſtants by the Name of Canonical, he fully with all his heart, and all his ſoul, believes them to be of Divine Authority, and none other then the Word of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 26. page of his <hi>Youngling Elder,</hi> 
               <q>he doth diſtinguiſh and lay down a double ſenſe and acceptation of the word Scripture, and in the one ſenſe clearly acknowledgeth them to be of Divine Authority, and ſo the foundation of Chriſtian Religion, onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them to be ſuch in the other ſenſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in that ſenſe here denyed by this Author, his learned Oponent Mr. <hi>William jenkin</hi> doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to be both of Divine Authority and the Word of God, diſallowing that diſtinction made by our Author, demanding <q>How any can believe the matter and ſubſtance of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be the Word of God, when he muſt be uncertain whether the written Word or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wherein the matter is contained, are the Word of God or no.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170139:13"/>
            <p>Now although both theſe learned men do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Scripture to be of Divine Authority the Word of God, yet it is ſo, that the one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it to be ſuch in one ſenſe, and the other in another ſenſe, neither of them allowing it to be ſuch in the others ſenſe nor yet producing any competent proof to evidence it to be ſuch in his own ſenſe. The truth of it in either ſenſe muſt ſtill therefore remain much (the more) to be doubted and that from theſe grounds and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe the Scripture, as it came from the Original Pen-men, was then (if at all) of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority, &amp; the word of God to the world; but it was not ſo then, being in an unknown Tongue, to the generality of man-kind; and therefore according to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine was (both in form, matter and ſubſtance) ſo far from being ſuch that it was meer <hi>Barbariſm</hi> to them 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.11. And if any urge. That it was afterward made of Divine Authority, and the Word of God to all by its being tranſlated into all Languages; here I demand, What humane Power could confer upon Tranſlations that Prerogative which the Authograph never had, eſpecially ſince all Tranſlations have many ſuch Errors, Miſtakes, and Contradictions in them as the Authographs had not, and as the Word of God cannot have; for to affirm any thing not perfectly true and infallible, to be the Word of God, implyes a flat contradiction.</p>
            <p>Beſides, herein alſo is a great failer, (namely) in that the moſt learned are at great variance, not certainly knowing, but much diſagreeing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170139:14"/>about the right ſenſe and meaning of words in Scripture; this is evident by their often chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, altering, amending and new making of the Bible; and by the palpable material differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and contradictions which ſtill remain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Traaſlations when all is done, and the many exceptions taken by ſome or other of the learned againſt every Tranſlation.</p>
            <p>Nay, if the original Language were the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Tongue of ſome amongſt us, yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would not be much the eaſier to them; and a natural <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Jew</hi> can with no more reaſon or authority obtrude any Tranſlation upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens conſciences then any other man of any other Nation can do.</p>
            <p>Conſider further the infinite variety of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations of the Bible that were in the primitive Ages of the Church (as St. <hi>Hierome</hi> obſerves) and never a one like another: And can any man think, but that the moſt learned of theſe later ages have differed, erred, and be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken as much in Tranſlations as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and that the <hi>medium</hi> is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain to theſe as it was to them, which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſeen by the great variety of late Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Commentaries, which are too pregnant an Argument, that the moſt learned neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the underſtanding of the words, nor of the ſenſe: and therefore Tranſlations can bind no man to believe them to be of Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or the Word of God; for an unknown, or uncertain ſenſe binds men as little to the belief thereof, as an unknown tongue doth; this alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ſets forth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.7, 8. in theſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170139:14"/>words, <hi>Even things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>without life giving ſound, whether Pipe or Harp, except it give a certain diſtinction in the ſound, how ſhall it be known what is piped or harped; for if the trumpet give an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſound, who ſhall prepare himſelf to Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe the Word of God, or Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt, which was of Divine Authority, and which univerſally concern'd and bound all men to believe it ſo to be, came not in any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue, nor upon any ſuch uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to any; nor only in plainneſs of ſpeech to be rightly underſtood of the meaneſt, vulgar, rational capacity, but with divine and evident demonſtration to atteſt the certain truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as may be ſeen in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſion to the <hi>Corinths</hi> (beſides many other places of like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.5. where he tells them, That his ſpeech and his preaching came not to them with perſwaſible words of mans wiſdom (only intelligible to them all but with evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of God, that there faith might not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the Power of God; evidently implying, That if it had come to them only in never ſo great plainneſs and wiſdom of ſpeech, and they had thereupon believed it, that then their Faith had ſtood meerly in the wiſdom of men, and not in the Word and Power of God.</p>
            <p>Now let it be conſidered, whether St. <hi>Pauls</hi> meer preaching (ſo as aforeſaid) be not of as much Divine Authority, and the Word of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170139:15"/>as any of his own or other mens writings in Scripture are, or ever were.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe the Word of God is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. for God did but ſay, <hi>Let there be light,</hi> and there was light; <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.3. Chriſt did ſay, <hi>Lazarus come forth; and the dead came forth bound hand and foot, Joh.</hi> 11.44. Theſe words &amp; actions were afterwards recorded, and ſo became Scripture. The words and acts of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were afterwards recorded, &amp; ſo became Scripture. The words and acts of the Devil (in his tempting of Chriſt in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) were afterwards recorded, and ſo became Scripture. But as the record of the words and acts of the Devil, are not the words and acts of the Devil; and as the record of the words and acts of the Kings of Iſrael, are not the words and acts of the Kings of Iſrael; ſo the writing or recording of Gods Words, is not Gods Word, but only a Declaration what was Gods Word whereby he created the Light, not that it is Gods VVord ſo written, or ſo read, or ſo ſpoken by us; for if it continue truly and indeed Gods VVord in our mouths, it muſt then ſtill powerfully produce Light when ſpoken by us, as then it did when it was ſpoken by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>And the like evident difference was in the Power that followed the Faith that was built upon the very VVord of God, above any faith that is built upon the Scripture in any ſenſe: Theſe ſigns followed the firſt (namely) The ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the mouths of Lyons; quenching the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170139:15"/>of fire; caſting out of Devils; ſpeaking with new Tongues; healing of the ſick by meer laying on of hands, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11.33, 34. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17, 18. But no ſuch ſigns follow the Faith built upon the Scripture, or on the matter and ſubſtance contained therein, nor on the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines drawn from them by any men, who uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally borrow or ſteal the words of God, of Chriſt, of the Prophets, of the Apoſtles, or any other which they there find recorded; and then (by the help of ſome Commentor, whereof there are divers and many) deviſe ſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they afterwards deliver as from God to the people. But ſuch would appear to deal more ingenuouſly if they did follow the Prophets advice, He that had onely a dream, ſhould tell it but as a dream, and not as the Word of God; for what is the chaff to the wheat? <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28, 29, 30, 31, 32.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially, I conceive it would be much more pleaſing to God, beneficial to men, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to themſelves not to trouble the world with any ſublime and myſterious Doctrine, as that of Trinity, Election, Predeſtination, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; the Nature or Eſſence of God; the order or number of his Decrees; the nature or extent of Chriſt his death, Juſtification, or any other matters in Divinity, ſo much controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among School-men, and other of the learned, and are but doubtfully and uncertainly known to the wiſeſt of them all, as is evident, in that each oppoſite among them with great confidence maintains the verity of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral contradictory Propoſitions in theſe Points,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170139:16"/>which is no marvel, ſince we ſee them likewiſe at no ſmall variance, even about the very Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Doctrine of Chriſt, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle reckoneth but as Milk for Babes, who are unskilful in the word of righteouſneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12, 13, 14 &amp; 6.1, 2. And would it not then be much wiſdom in them ſo far to obſerve the prophilbiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt to his Apoſtless (<hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4.8.) as to forbear teaching theſe points un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they were undoubtedly aſſured of the truth of them themſelves, and endued with power from on high evidently to demonſtrate the verity of them to other men, wherby to convince them. And in the mean time to teach men altogether ſuch practical points as are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to every rational mans underſtanding and conſcience (wherein they would find work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, much more profitable) as to the forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of all kind of wicked, ſinful, diſhoneſt and deceitful dealings in their lives and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; together with all kind of tyranny, cruelty, oppreſſion, injuſtice, pride, high and earthly-mindedneſs, covetouſneſs (which is Idolatry and the root of all evil) drunkenneſs, and all other abuſes of the good creatures of God in any kind of exceſs whatſoever, ſuffering in the mean time many of their poor Brethren to pine away and ſtarve for want of neceſſaries, and on the contrary excite them to the diligent and conſtant practiſe of all honeſt, virtuous, pious, juſt, charitable, good and conſcionable living, to the exerciſing mercy, love and peace towards all men, and to a deſpiſing of the riches, honors and glories of this world, ſhewing them the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170139:16"/>and deceitfulneſs of them, and the many thouſand great evils and miſchiefs which they certainly bring upon the lovers and poſſeſſors of them.</p>
            <p>Hereby undoubtedly many great benefits would accrue unto themſelves alwayes provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that indeed and in truth they reform their own affections and converſations according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is abſolutely neceſſary in the caſe.</p>
            <p>For firſt, Hereby they would free themſelves from all the juſt contempts, gainſayings, and contradictions both of the <hi>Quakers</hi> &amp; all other men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, inſtead of mens envying, hating, and perſecuting one another (being now the uſual product of their teachings) they would breed amity, peace and concord amongſt men, and (in all likelyhood) make their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons generally to conſiſt of pious, honeſt, juſt and good men, full of all courteous and civil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment toward all, both at home and abroad, which would be no ſmall Ornament, Honor &amp; Benefit, both to the place wherein they live, and to the Commonwealth whereof they are Members.</p>
            <p>And now for further illuſtration of the point in hand, let us conſider, That when the Word of the Lord came to the Prophets of old, and vvhen they had delivered it as Gods Word to them to vvhom it vvas ſent, and vvhen it had diſpatched the buſineſs for vvhich it came, then,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170139:17"/>and not till then both it, and its event was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, and ſo became Scripture; now though it was the Word of the Lord both when it came, and vvhen it vvas delivered to them to vvhom it vvas ſent; yet it may be queſtioned whether it continued ſo in the writing of it; I vvill inſtance only in the Prophet <hi>Jonah,</hi> to whom the Word of the Lord came, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ariſe and go to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and to cry and preach againſt it theſe words, <hi>viz. Yet forty dayes, and Nineveh ſhall be overthrown:</hi> He went and did ſo, whereupon they repented; all which was aftervvard vvritten, and ſo became Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But if the ſame Prophet in like manner had preached the ſame words to the ſame City any time after they had repented, then it had been falſe, and no Word of God at all unto them; hovv then can it reaſonably be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Word of God, either to that City, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, only by its being written, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Scripture, but to be meerly as a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what was the Word of God which he once ſent by his Prophet to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> upon which they repented, and ſo eſcaped the Judgement threatned. Nay, ſuppoſe the ſame City had ſoon after relapſed into the the ſame ſins, yet the ſame Prophet could not (without ſin) have preached the ſame words as Gods VVord unto them, nor yet have pronounced the ſame Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor any other, as from the Lord, againſt them, vvithout ſome new Commiſſion, which might have been to pronounce ſome other Judgement, or to have ſome ſhorter time allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for Repentance. Many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170139:17"/>come under the like conſideration.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Becauſe the Famine thratned by the Prophet, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11, 12. that the Lord would ſend, that men ſhould wander from ſea to ſea, from the North even to the Eaſt, and run to and fro to ſeek the word of the Lord and ſhould not find it, cannot be underſtood of Scriptures, or Bibles; nay, it were well if we had not cauſe to fear from the Apoſtles Prophecy 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. and from experience, That that, or the like Famine hath befalne Chriſtiendom it ſelf, even where, and when Bibles, (with its matter and ſubſtance) Profeſſors and Teachers have been moſt plentiful: See and conſider if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other then Chriſtian Profeſſors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers can be meant by that propheſie of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, Becauſe whereas it is ſaid 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.1. That the Word of the Lord was precious in thoſe dayes, this is not meant that Scripture or Bibles was then ſearce, for the text renders the reaſon thereof to be, becauſe there was no open viſion; So where it is often mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Scripture of <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers making inquiry of the Lord, and of the Word of the Lord in matters of difficulty, this is not meant, that they had recourſe to the Bible or Scripture, for if that had been the meaning, then <hi>Saul</hi> needed not in his diſtreſs to have ſought to the Witch at <hi>Ender</hi> to help him to the ſpeech with <hi>Samuel,</hi> that ſo he might of him enquire the Word of the Lord. Nor if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170139:18"/>after the ſeeking to God by prayer, the propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city or bent of mens ſpirits were the anſwer or Word of the Lord, then <hi>Balaam</hi> by taking that courſe to know the mind of God, had not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the advancement propoſed to him by the King, nor of being King himſelf, if that had been the queſtion and the deſire and motion of his heart after his ſeeking God by prayer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, had been the anſwer to that queſtion; and to be taken as the voice, word and anſwer of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And indeed, the offer of ſuch great prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and honor in this world by <hi>Balaack,</hi> was a great temptation to <hi>Balaam;</hi> but the offer of Kingdoms of this world, and the glory of them, was a temptation of the devils own invention, &amp; ſufficient enough in his judgment to have entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and by conſequence to have overthrown Chriſt himſelf, and ſo to have fruſtrated all his glorious deelared purpoſes &amp; deſignes of freeing mankind from all kind of bondage and ſlavery whatſoever, and inſtead thereof, to have made him become ſubſervient to him, to keep men under all the ſlaveries wherein they were invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; yea and to become a chief ſupporter of all ſubordinate corrupt intereſts of worldly and wicked men, whereby (as the devils inſtruments) they unjuſtly hold their Fellow-brethren as captives in oppreſſion &amp; ſlavery; It is therefore to be lamented, when at any time we ſee him thrive in any ſuch devilliſh project. The Lord in mercy deliver every honeſt man from being overcome by any ſuch temptation; <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170139:18"/>
            <p>But to find the word &amp; anſwer of God (in the way aforementioned) may apear to be very uncertain by this, <hi>viz.</hi> If four pious men ſhould each of them ſeek by prayer for an anſwer from God in one and the ſame thing, be it of publicke concernment, or otherwiſe, wherein their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, judgements and perſwaſions are different and various each from other; you will find the propencity and bent of their hearts and deſires after prayer, for the moſt part will vary as much as before, which will manifeſt this to be no ſound or ſure way to find out or know the word or anſwer of God; nor is this intended to diſcourage any from ſeeking to the Lord in any occaſion, but from truſting to the bent of their own hearts to be any ſure Rule to know the anſwer of God by; becauſe, that may be the effect of ſome pride or vain deſire of wordly glory, or of ſome other luſt ſecretly lurking in the heart of man undiſcerned, for the heart of man being deceitful above all things, who then can know his own heart, or the ſecret turnings thereof? <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.10.11. or who can ſay his heart is ſo pure and clean, as to be quite purged from all kind of vain, carnal, and eatthly affection, and luſt, he muſt then be no longer a man, having fleſh, blood, or any other infirmity like other men on earth, but be equal to the pureſt Angel in heaven.</p>
            <p>And now having propoſed &amp; left theſe things to conſideration, we will proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Mr. <hi>R Baxter,</hi> a man of Eminency both for exquiſite learning &amp; parts, in his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> Part. 2. pag. 201. of the ſixth Edition tells us, thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170139:19"/>
            <p>R.B. <hi>That Divine Faith hath ever a Divine F<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi> And in page 205. thus; <hi>We muſt know it to be a Divine Testimony, before we can believe</hi> Fide Divina And in page 211. he ſaith, <hi>As Tranſlations are no further Scripture then they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Copies in the Original Tongues; ſo neither are theſe Copies further then they agree with the Authographs, or original Copies, or with ſome Copies peruſed and approved by the Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it is a thing worth the knowing of this Author, Whether he, or any man elſe, can infallibly produce the Authographs, or any ſuch original Copies of the Bible as have been ſo peruſed and approved of by the Apoſtles, and if none can do this, how can they then prove any Copie or Tranſlation to be true (or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as he phraſeth it?) And if any can do this, how ſhall it be known to be ſuch without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Evidence undoubtedly to prove it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But to this he gives us a general anſwer in his Preface to his Book of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> where he tells us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.B.</hi> 
               <q>That the Holy Ghoſt by ſpecial inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the Author of the Scriptures, and by extraordinary Endowments was the Author of the miracles which were wrought for its confirmation.</q> 
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But here it is neceſsary, that he tells us where, when, &amp; by whom thoſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were wrought which ſo confirmed the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And in the ſecond place he ſhould tell us where, &amp; which are thoſe Scriptures that were ſo confirmed; &amp; withal, to produce ſome Divine Evidence to prove what he therein ſayes, before any wiſe man believe him; for he himſelf in his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170139:19"/>
               <hi>Reſt,</hi> Pag. 201. before cited, informs us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi> That <hi>to believe implicitely, That the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony is Divine, or the Scripture is the Word of God, this is not to believe God, but to reſolve our faith into ſome humane Teſtimony, even to lay our foundation upon the Sand, where all will fall at the next aſſault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding in Pag 238. &amp; 239. of his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> before mentioned, he tells us,</p>
            <p>R.B. <hi>That ſomething muſt be taken upon truſt from man whether we will or no, yet no uncertainty in our faith neither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, 1. ſaith he, <hi>The meer illitterate man muſt take it upon truſt, that the Book is a Bible which he hears read, for elſe he knows not but it may be ſome other Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> What! may he not take it ſo upon truſt that the Book is a Bible and yet never the more know but it may be ſome other Book? or doth not a mans ſimple taking a thing (eſpecially of ſuch high concernment) ſo groundleſly upon truſt, argue ſome diminution of his knowledg and wiſdom too, rather then any augmentation of either.</p>
            <p>R. B. 2. <hi>That theſe words are in it which the Reader pronounceth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That it is tranſlated truly out of the Original Languages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> How can it be tranſlated truly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly, or imperfectly and truly? for in pag. 211. of the ſame Book he poſitively aſſerts,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170139:20"/>That there is an impoſſibility that any Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould perfectly expreſs the ſenſe of the Original.</p>
            <p>R. B. 4. <hi>That the Hebrew and Greek Copies out of which it was tranſlated, are true authentick Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That it was originally written in theſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Yea, and the meaning of divers Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſages, which cannot be underſtood without the knowledge of Jewiſh (uſtoms, of Cronology, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>though the words were never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o exactly tranſlated; all theſe, with many more, the vulgar muſt take upon the word of their Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Alas poor Vulgars! what miſerable hard tasks are here impoſed upon you, and almoſt all men, with a muſt? much like thoſe put upon the children of Iſrael, to make their full tale of brick, without any allowance of ſtraw, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they were put to take up any ſtubble where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they could find it? But can any wiſe man take theſe Doctrines to be divine, or come from God, they being ſo irrational and abſurd, and ſo contrary to him and his wayes, who oppoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Goſpel to be diſpenſed (not in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue, or upon any ſuch uncertainties to any, but) to all people in their own language, himſelf alſo evidently and powerfully atteſting the ſame, otherwiſe he obligeth no man to take it for truth, nor blameth any man for taking it otherwiſe.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170139:20"/>
            <p>And whereas he poſitively aſſerts in pag. 211. of his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> as before is noted;</p>
            <p>R. B. <hi>That there is an impoſſibility that any Tranſlation ſhould perfectly expreſs the ſenſe of the Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. It's now incumbent on him to tell us whether it was the expreſſable imperfect ſenſe in Tranſlations, or the unexpreſſable perfect ſenſe of the Original that was ſo confirmed by miracles; or whether it was all, or any of thoſe many books which are mentioned in Scripture (and whereof we have neither original nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py) that were ſo confirmed; plain dealing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in would be very ſatisfactory, and is even more then neceſſary.</p>
            <p>In his book of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> Part 1. Pag. 11. he tells us, That</p>
            <p>R. B. <hi>Beſides the ſanctifying Spirit of Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Goſpel-times, there is alſo a miraculous pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Spirit proper to the firſt age of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How is miraculous pouring out of the Spirit proper to the firſt age of the Church, when as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf affirms and proves by <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and others, that it continued in the Church three or four hundred yeers at leaſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And in pag. 31. he gives a reaſon why Chriſt would then thus convincingly ſend abroad ſuch aboundance of the Spirit, namely, Becauſe <hi>he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170139:21"/>had the old Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>to repeal, and that was well known by the Jews to be Gods own, and men muſt not believe Gods Law ceaſed or abrogated without proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Are there not yet many thouſands of the Jews that adhere to the old Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and remain ſtill in unbelief? And was not the Goſpel miraculouſly confirmed to the Gentiles, who owned not <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, as well, and as much, and more then it was to the Jews.</p>
            <p>And in page 32. 33. among many other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt any ſuch miraculous uſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to continue in the Church, he gives two.</p>
            <p>R.B. 1. <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we have the full uſe and benefit of the holy Ghoſt, which was given then; that ſeal that was then ſet to the Chriſtian Doctrine and Scriptures, ſtands there ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is it to all the various and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting Doctrines and Scriptures in the world that this ſeal is ſet, and ſtands there ſtill, or to ſome only? and if but to ſome, how may a man undoubtedly know to which of them that ſeal is ſet, and to which not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.B.</hi> 2. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt doth ſtill continue his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to his Churches, and every true member thereof, but not the ſame uſe, and therefore not to enable them to the ſame work as then; Tongues are not for them that believe, but for them that believe not</hi> (ſaith Paul) 1 Cor. 14. 22. <hi>that is to ſhow the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170139:21"/>power of Chriſt, and ſo convince them; but now the Scripture is ſealed by theſe, there is not the ſame uſe or need of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It's true, the ſpirit was given and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to true Churches, and every Member thereof, but not without manifeſtation; for the manifeſtation of the Spirit was given to every one to profit withal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. as well as the Spirit it ſelf; for how elſe can any true Church or Member be known from falſe, ſince all differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſects and ſorts of Chriſtians pretend to have the Spirit; yea, and this learned Author, with all his learned Oponents (no doubt) do conceive themſelves to be true Members of the true Church, &amp; ſo each of them to have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, notwithſtanding the many great and vaſt differences between them in the moſt material and eſſential points of the Goſpel, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with their having the Spirit, whoſe Office is to evince truth, and to lead into all truth; beſides this Author himſelf in his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> Par. 2 pag. 206. <hi>aſſerts, That he hath ſtill known thoſe that pretend to the ſtrongeſt ſenſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Revelations, to have proved the moſt wicked and deluded perſons in the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, where ſee we in any that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt power which alwayes did, and muſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany thoſe that had this Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.37.38. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.17.18.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.12.16. <hi>Heb</hi> 2.4. <hi>Lu.</hi> 24 49. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7.8. but the uſe and need of this power is now denyed by this Author, and by many other, who yet retain the form of godlineſs, even as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> long ſince
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170139:22"/>foretold that ſuch ſhould be in theſe laſt days, &amp; even then alſo injoined true Chriſtians from all ſuch to turn away, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.5. Wherefore I conceive it would be very raſh for any man to believe this Author while he alledgeth that the Scripture is ſealed by the former powerful works of the Spirit, untill ſome ſuch powerful Works can be produced by him to evince the verity thereof; and likewiſe, in the ſame manner, to evince and ſet forth undoubtedly which, or what Scripture it is (of all the many varius ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures now extant in the world) that is ſo ſealed, wherby it may certainly be known &amp; diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all the reſt; for this alſo is abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, unleſs his meaning be, that all Scripture whatſoever is ſo ſealed. And whereas he here tells us, That the gift of Tongues was for them that believe not, to convince them; hence it will follow, That as long as there are unbelievers in the world to be convinced, ſo long the gifts of Tongues is neceſſary for that end.</p>
            <p>And in Part 2. pag. 36 he gives another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diſcontinuance of that Divine Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and powerfull convincement, in telling us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B. That miracles would looſe their convincing force and be no miracles if they were common to all, and in all ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet in Par. 3. pag. 242. 243. he tells us, <hi>That it is certain from current teſtimony, &amp; Church-Records, That the gift of caſting out devils &amp; making them confeſs themſelves maſtered by Chriſt, did remain in the Church three or four hundred yeers at leaſt after
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170139:22"/>the Apoſtles.</hi> And for this he there produceth many Authors, and after ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No where could Satan keep his poſſeſſion, where the power of Christ did aſſault him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in his Saints Reſt, Part 2. pag. 232. he cites the words of ſome of thoſe Authors, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us,</p>
            <p>R. B. <hi>That</hi> Irenaeus <hi>affirmeth, That in his time the working of miracles, the raiſing of the dead, the casting out of Devils, healing of the ſick by meer laying on of hands, by propheſying, were in force, and that ſome that were ſo raiſed from death remained alive among them long after; and that</hi> Cyprian <hi>and</hi> Turtul <hi>mentioned the ordinary casting out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and challenge the Heathen to come and ſee it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Since miracles (as is confeſt) were common, not only in the firſt age in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, but for four hundred years at leaſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet loſt not their convincing force, nor ceaſed to be miracles, why then might they not have continued in the ages ſince, without lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their convincing force or ceaſing to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles?</p>
            <p>And if without any abſurdity a man may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm (as no doubt but he may) that for thoſe 400. years after the Apoſtles theſe miraculous and powerfull gifts were uſeful and neceſſary, then he may with as little abſurdity affirm and maintain, That they were ſince, and are ſtill uſeful and neceſſary, even for the very ſame ends and porpoſes; for Miracles or Tongues (as was ſaid by this Author) are not for them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170139:23"/>but for them that believe not; and are there not ſtill Heathens, Infidels, Jews, Turks, Pagans, Sorcerers, Witches, Conjurors, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in abundance of all ſorts, many ſpiritual Wickedneſſes in High Places now in the world, as wel as then, and infinite numbers of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> now as were not then? And are there not in the world a numberleſs number of all ſorts and ſects of Chriſtians, of various Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, different intereſts and perſwaſions, yet each pretend to have the Spirit, and be in the Truth, and therefore condemn all the reſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom may be found more wicked, baſe, tyrannical, bloody, cruel, covetous, and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſons then ordinarily among the Heathen themſelves, witneſs the many Perſecutions, Wars, Maſſacres, Murtherings; Poyſonings, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinations, Burnings, Killings, and other ways of deſtroying of mankind, from, and among thoſe called Chriſtians, and in particular, the cruel burnings and deſtroyings of men in queen <hi>Marys</hi> dayes, in England; the many maſſacred and deſtroyed in <hi>France;</hi> the bloody Inquiſition in Spain; the unheard of Cruelties exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Engliſh by the Dutch in <hi>Amboyna;</hi> the moſt monſtrous abominable bloody cruelties done by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in deſtroying many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of harmleſs creatures, men women and children in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> ſpoyling, robbing, and depriving them cauſleſly both of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Countries and lives, and that ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly and barbarouſly, that it is ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to make the very name of a Chriſtian to ſtink all the world over, &amp; as by report in ſome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170139:23"/>forraign parts, even among <hi>Mahometans</hi> it doth, where they uſe to ſay upon occaſion one to another <hi>[What doſt thou think I am a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to ſwear, lye, cozen, and deceive thee]</hi> this is ſoon credited by ſuch as know any thing of the manifold myſterious frauds and over-reachings uſually practiſed in tradings and commerce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Chriſtendom it ſelf: For,</p>
            <p>Are there not among them Publicans and Harlots, yea, and many Whole-ſale-Thieves, who rob and impoveriſh many men at one clap by getting great ſtore of Wealth into their hands upon credit, and then break, and ſo cheat them all at once, and be ſafe by getting ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in ſome Church, Priſon, or other preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Protection?</p>
            <p>Nay, have there not been ſome Whole-ſale-Thieves in Office and Authority, who beggar Particular men and families at once by col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of Law and Juſtice, and yet eſcape ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, when in the mean time ſome ſo beggared or impoveriſhed, do but ſteal to ſupply natures neceſſity, ſhall be judged to death, when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the fault is moſt in the Government or in the Governors under which they live, either in not puniſhing ſuch great Thieves according to their demerit, and cauſing reſtitution to be made, or at leaſt, in not making ſome Proviſion for the neceſſary ſupply of all ſuch as are brought into unavoidable neceſſity &amp; ſtreights, even as God commanded the Jews, <hi>Levi.</hi> 25 35. <hi>if thy brother be waxen poor, and fallen to decay with thee, then thou ſhall relieve him; yea though he be a ſtranger, or ſojourner, that he may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170139:24"/>live with thee;</hi> and that all ſuch ſhould be much indulged, is both reaſonable, and according to Scripture, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.30. <hi>Men do not deſpiſe a thief,</hi> much leſs revile him, (and leſt of all ought they to hang him) <hi>if he ſteal, to ſatisfie his ſoul when he is hungery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is there not in ſome places Juſtice and Right ordinarily ſo hard to be got through multiplicity of Mizmazes, Intanglements, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricaties, quirks and Colluſions diviſed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by crafty and unconſcionable Lawyers Clerks, <hi>&amp;c</hi> whereby Cauſes are uſually protra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, Clyents perplexed, their Purſes dreined, and their Remedy made worſe then their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, to the undoing of many; how then can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinary or poor man think to be able to get Juſtice that way wherein the rich are ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently made beggars by ſeeking it, and go without it too, when all is done.</p>
            <p>For, may not ſome be ſeen thus ſpoiled by the injuſtice of ordinary Courts, who thereupon appealing to the chief Magiſtrate and ſupremeſt Power (the only means left them) for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life, and after diſcoveries made of much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice done them, and after many fair words and promiſes of redreſs, may not ſome nevertheleſs be yet ſeen ſtill languiſhing without help, yea, and after many years ſpent in tedious and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable attendances whereby their grievances are more then trebbled upon them: And may not ſome ſuch be yet ſeen (with much ſadneſs and affliction of ſpirit) ſtill attending and ſtill languiſhing under all theſe oppreſſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any the leaſt eaſe or relief.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170139:24"/>
            <p>And indeed, where can be ſeen any King or chief Magiſtrate to lay the heavy burthens and grievances of the people ſo to heart, as out of pity, conſcience, or good diſpoſition to eaſe and disburthen them, or ſo much as effectually to reform the aforeſaid abominations after they be diſcovered ſo offenſive to honeſt, wiſe, and vertuous men, and ſo great a ſhame to any Chriſtian-Commonwealth to permit, and more then any man, having power in his hand, with any true fear of God in his heart, can poſſibly endure.</p>
            <p>Theſe, with innumerable other great and horrid wickedneſſes, are perpetrated among the ſons of men, yea, and ſome ſuch too in Chtiſtendom, as would make a meer moraliz'd Heathen bluſh to hear; wherefore it is ſtrange to me, that any ſuch conſiderate wiſe man ſhould think, much leſs in print affirm, That there is no uſe or need now of thoſe powerfull gifts of the Spirit to convince this Reprobate and ungodly world, and to bring them from all theſe wicked and ſinfull practiſes unto true faith and repentance, that ſo they may become true and real Chriſtians, not in name only (as the preſent mode is) but in deed and in truth; and in particular, convincingly to reveal to all Kings and chief Magiſtrats the greatneſs of their ſin and wickedneſs in permitting, and not remedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aforeſaid practiſes and oppreſſions, which are ſo hateful to God and all good men.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170139:25"/>
            <p>And it is yet more ſtrange to me, that any ſuch man ſhould ſo much neglect and over-ſee all Experience in this and late ages, as to think that the uſual flatteries of meer Pulpit-Sermons by Trencher-Champlains, or any Mercenary Clergy, or others who generally have mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, preach for filthy lucres ſake, and are no ſmall corrupt intereſt themſelves, living deliciouſly by the ſweat of other mens brows, will ever effect this Divine and powerful work in the world; let him believe it that can, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve even what I might poſſibly deſire to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; their converſation, their actions muſt work it in me.</p>
            <p>R. B. And in his <hi>Saints reſt,</hi> part 2. pag. 236. he hath theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>I demand with my ſelf By what argument did <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> evince to the world the verity of their doctrine; and I find it was chiefly by this of miracles; and ſurely Chriſt knew the beſt argument to prove the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of his doctrine; and that which was the beſt then, is the beſt ſtill.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſoon after he uſeth theſe words, namely, <hi>Doth not Chriſt ſay, If I had not done the works that no man elſe could do, ye had not had ſinne;</hi> (that is) <hi>Your not believing me to be the Meſſiah had been no ſin, for no man is bound to believe that which was never convincingly revealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> This Author by his aſſerting here that Chriſt did evince to the world the verity of his Doctrine by Miracles, and that he ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170139:25"/>knew the beſt Argument to prove the divine Authority of his Doctrine; and by his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thence, That that which was the beſt then, is the beſt ſtill, had almoſt made me think that he intended a perfect agreement with the truth which all along he had oppoſed, but that I found him preſently to falſifie that Text in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15 24. in like manner as he had done the ſame Text in many other places, <hi>viz.</hi> In leaving out the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis thereof even that which chiefly corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and upheld that truth which in his prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent aſſertion he ſeemingly maintained; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in omitting theſe words, <hi>viz. Among them, and that they did both ſee and hate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for the Text is, <hi>If I had done among them, &amp;c.</hi> (that is, in their preſence that they might both ſee and hear the Miracles done by Chriſt, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did thoſe that were done by <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8.6.) <hi>they had not had ſin; but now have they beth ſeen and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both me and my Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And with the like unfaithfulneſs doth he bring up the Rear in the words following by omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to add <hi>[to him]</hi> by which it is made neither current nor found; for if St. <hi>Paul</hi> were now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and had convincingly revealed the Goſpel to many thouſand men, and not to me, this (though it bound them to believe, yet it) binds not me, to whom it was never convincingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; but when ever it is convincingly reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me, as well as to them, then it binds me, as well as them, but not elſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe bawks are not comely in any man, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if in the leaſt he pretends ſincerity; for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170139:26"/>as the ſin of the Scribes and Phariſees there, was much aggravated by their ſeeing and hating, ſo is every mans elſe (though not in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) that ſhall ſee this, or any other Text flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt his purpoſe, and then to cite it ſo maimedly, as to make it ſpeak againſt the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or genuine ſenſe thereof (as by this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor this is often cited) whereby to make Chriſt, whoſe words they were, to bear falſe witneſs ſo much againſt himſelf and his truth, this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive is no ſmall offence, nor is this any other then a friendly caution, that when ever this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is again handled, both Chriſt, his truth, and this Text may be better dealt with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi> And whereas this Author here tells us from current Teſtimony, <hi>That the gift of caſting out Devils, and making them confeſs themſelves maſtered by Chriſt, did remain in the Church for three or four hundred yeers at leaſt after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and that Satan could no where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eep his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, where this power of Chriſt did aſſault him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then let it be conſidered:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> 1. Whether there be not many Pagan Nations whereof Satan hath full poſſeſſion, and wherein he is worſhipped by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants as God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether he hath not in all Nations, places and perſons, ſome large poſſeſſion, at leaſt in their hearts, by envy, pride, covetouſneſs, or ſome other baſe affection and luſt.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170139:26"/>
            <p>And ſhall any ſuch man yet think that there is not now need or uſe of theſe powerful gifts of the Spirit to diſpoſſeſs this powerful Prince that yet ſo ruleth in the world and hearts of men? Or can he, or any man elſe be ſo ſimple, as to think that Satan ever was, or yet is ſo weak or fooliſh, as to be ſcared and caſt out of any of all theſe his ſtrong holds, meerly by the various, uncertain, and contrary holy winds, blown from Pulpits by artificial Divines, any more then he ever was or will be caſt out of any place or perſon by vertue of holy Water ſprinkled by Fryars or Monks.</p>
            <p>Wherefore for theſe and many other good cauſes it may be well deem'd, That there was ſince the ſaid four hundred yeers, and is yet, the ſame need of the ſaid powerful gifts of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as were formerly given by Chriſt to his Church, notwithſtanding all, or any thing ſaid by this learned Author to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Dan. Featly</hi> another Doctor in Divinity, and famed for a great Schollar; in his <hi>Dippers Dipt,</hi> pag. 1. likewiſe plainly tells us, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Tranſlation is ſimply authentical, or the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Word of God; in the undoubted Word of God there can be no error, but in Tranſlations there may be, and are errors. The Bible tranſlated (therefore) is not the undoubted Word of God, but ſo far onely as it agreeth with the Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe paſſages coming forth by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as licenced Vertues, if the learned Licencer
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170139:27"/>know any; and this Argument being approved as ſound and good by other of the learned in my hearing, I cannot chuſe but query thus of my own underſtanding, or of any mans elſe that hath charity and ability to inform me better.</p>
            <p>Whether the very ſame Argument, upon the very ſame grounds and reaſons, may not in like manner be enforc't againſt all Copies whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in any Language whatſoever, as well and as truly as againſt Tranſlations? thus: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Copy is ſimply authentical, or the undoubted Word of God; in the undoubted Word of God there can be no Error, but in Copies there may be, and are Errors. The Bible copyed (therefore) is not the undoubted Word of God, but ſo far onely as it agree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h with the Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, although it be admitted by many that the original Pen-men of the Scripture were all inſpired by God, yet it may be, and is by all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, that the Copyers thereof were any more inſpired then the Tranſlators, but that they might erre, and have erred as well as Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors as before is manifeſt) how elſe came there ſuch diverſities of Copies into the world as well as of Tranſlations?</p>
            <p>And whereas in the concluſion of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is implyed, That ſo far as either Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Copy can be proved to agree with the Original ſo far only it is to be accounted the Word of God: Whence I query.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether it be poſſible for any to produce the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted ſeveral Originals of the ſeveral Books of the Bible, or undoubtedly to know them if it were poſſible to produce them, they being written by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170139:27"/>perſons, in divers places, in diver ages, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs Languages, and upon divers occaſions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if none be able to do this, I then query,</p>
            <p>How it can be poſſible for any undoubtedly to prove any Book, Chapter or Verſe, either of Tranſlation or Copy to agree with the Original.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſeeing reaſon &amp; experience teach, That time produceth ſuch variations and changes in languages, as that a word ſignifying one thing in one age, may &amp; often hath another ſigniſication put upon it by uſe and cuſtom in another age; whence elſe is it, that ſome Hebrew and Greek words bears divers, ſome ſix, ſome ſeven, and ſome contrary ſignifications, as one word to ſignifie both to bleſs and to curſe in <hi>Job</hi> 2.9. And it cannot in reaſon be imagined, but that ſome words may have quite loſt their Original ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſince the firſt writing of the Bible; wherefore it would prove a very difficult work (if not impoſſible) for any to give to each paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and word its genuine ſenſe and undoubted ſignification, if it were poſſible (as it is not) that the very true originals might be both produced and known.</p>
            <p>For Reſolution in the Premiſes, conference being had with divers Schollars of eminent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for piety, learning, and ability in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, one whereof (with womaniſh frowardneſs) uſed altogether authoritative admonitions and cenſures inſtead of Argument and Reaſon, which was expected, and onely could ſatisfie. But the other no leſs learned, but much more inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous (acknowledging the charge in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to be juſt) anſwered. That notwithſtanding
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170139:28"/>the variations or contradictions, either in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, or in Tranſlations, yet they were all true in the ſubſtance; whereas the truth in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was not the doubt nor queſtion, but this, How the ſaid Copies or Tranſlations ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as aforeſaid, could, or can with any Juſtice or Reaſon be impoſed in each ſeveral Language, on each ſeveral Nation &amp; people, as the undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Word of God. And how the various Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Doctrines, and Concluſions drawn from theſe by their ſeveral and reſpective Miniſters, can be propoſed to the people in each ſeveral Nation, as the preaching of the true Goſpel of Chriſt and Word of God to be believed in for ſalvation; eſpecially conſidering how that their preaching is altogether fallible, ſeldom proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, often contradicting, and condemning one the other for erronious perſons, and Hereticks; and one the others Doctrine for Error and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas it is evident by theſe Scriptures we have that the true &amp; onely Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. or Word of God, being a great Myſtery was hid in God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9. and firſt delivered to Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.49, 50. who gave it to his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.8, 14. Whom he deligated as his Witneſſes and Embaſſadors, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.41. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing them to publiſh the ſame unto the world as Goſpel to every creature, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.42. Yet this their deligation or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was not compleat until they were endued with power from on high, by coming down of the holy Spirit upon them, <hi>Lu.</hi> 24.49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4. And when they were thus baptized with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170139:28"/>Spirit themſelves, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5. they then prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched this Word of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.25. or this Goſpel by the holy Spirit ſent down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.12. <hi>(i.e.)</hi> God confirming the Word, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.20. and bearing witneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to with ſigns and wonders, and divers miracles and gifts of the holy Spirit, <hi>Heb</hi> 2.4. Upon which infallible Teſtimony and evident Divine demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of God, was the Chriſtian faith and Churches then foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtles and true Miniſters; 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. and no other then the ſame Foundation can any man now lay, more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully then he may now preach any other Goſpel then the ſame that was then preached by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and true Miniſters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</p>
            <p>Nor did theſe only publiſh this Goſpel, or Word of God thus witneſſed, but did alſo in their Miniſtry propoſe the gifts of the Spirit to be promiſed to all believing the Goſpel, or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereby, both near, and afar off, <hi>Acts</hi> 2 38, 39. And they being made able Miniſters of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. did accordingly adminiſter the ſame by laying on of hands upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17, 18. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.5. making good the promiſe of Chriſt to all believers, that theſe ſignes ſhould follow them that believe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.17, 18. Thus were they all baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one body by one ſpirit, and were all made to drink into one ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>(i.e.)</hi> every one of this body had ſome manifeſt gift of the Spirit, whereby they became Members of that body to profit the body withal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.12.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170139:29"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. ſo as if any one had not ſome ſuch gift of the ſpirit, the ſame was none of Chriſts, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> none of that his body or Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of all which, puts me thus further to query.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether the ſaid Copyes or Tranſlations of the Bible, or any Doctrines or Concluſions drawn from thence by men fallible and ſubject to error and miſtake as other men are, be any other or more then humane Teſtimony, or ſo great as that of John Baptiſt, mentioned Joh.</hi> 1.27, 28, 29, 31, 36?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether all humane Teſtimony (even that of John Baptiſt among the reſt) was not rejected by Chriſt as an inſufficient ground for divine and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith to be built upon? Joh.</hi> 5.32, 33.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether did not Chriſt produce greater wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then that of</hi> John <hi>or any other humane Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, without which the ſons of men were not bound or required to believe?</hi> Joh. 5.36. Joh. 15.24. Joh. 10.37.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether any ought to be received for true Miniſters or Ambaſſadors of the Goſpel of Chriſt who ſeek their Ambaſſie out of Books or Libraries, or make the various Commentaries or Expoſitions of the ſaid Cop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es or Tranſlations, or their own or other mens Doctrines or Concluſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, the matter or ground of their Miniſtry or Embaſſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170139:29"/>5. <hi>Whether any ought to be received for true Miniſters or Ambaſſadors of the Goſpel of Christ who are not witneſſed to by evident demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of God, as aforeſaid, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reaſons thereof both in the Apoſtles time and ſince, are the ſame; ſo that if it was not then ſuperfluous, it was ſince, and is yet neceſſary, even for the ſame ends and purpoſes,</hi> Rom. 15.18, 19. Acts 8.6. &amp; 9 35, 42. &amp; 11.21. <hi>and if the ſaid witneſs of God was ſo abſolutely neceſſary to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Truth of Chriſts own Miniſtry, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it his own and other mens Teſtimony of him was invalid, and not to be believed, but might be waved without ſin, then no Miniſtry of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſince ought to be believed or received (as ſuch) upon eaſier or leſſer terms; for no ſervant is greater then his Maſter; but the firſt is true,</hi> Joh. 5.31.33, 34, 36. John 15.24. Joh. 10.37.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Whether any ought to be accounted true Churches, or Members of a true Church of Chriſt, who are deſtitute of the ſaid baptiſm of the ſpirit, or who make the ſaid fallible matter, or Miniſtry, or humane Teſtimony the ground of their faith? and where in Scripture can we find mention of any ſuch Church of Chriſt, it being moſt conſonant both to Scripture and Reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That every member of that body be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to its Head, in partaking of the Spirit in ſome meaſure, with manifeſtation, which Chriſt the Head received above meaſure, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ran down, or extended it ſelf to the whole body, &amp; to each member in particular, whereof
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170139:30"/>the Oyle poured on <hi>Aarons</hi> head, and running down to the very skirts of his Garment, was a lively type and figure. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the great ſtructure of Chriſtianity, whoſe Principle is. That a man at his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance therein ſhould be required to deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and to forſake all his worldly enjoyments in this life only on the aſſurance he then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives of the great glory and rewards promiſed in the life to come, ſhould then alſo have this faith of his eſtabliſhed upon Divine and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Evidence; leſs then which cannot be any ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground, nor prove better in this caſe to men, then the houſe mentioned by Chriſt did to the fooliſh builder, who built the ſame upon the earth without foundation, which ſuddenly fell, the fall whereof was very great, <hi>Lu.</hi> 6.49.</p>
            <p>When the Premiſes are duly weighed, it will be the leſs marvel that the Doctriens and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the moſt able, learned, and beſt men in the world have been, and are ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, full of cantradictions, and oppoſite one againſt another, as may appear to any that ſhall but look into the great controverſies that in all, or moſt ages that we hear of, have been holden and maintained both in Churches and Councils, and amongſt the moſt ſtudious Fathers, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Pen-men and Preachers in all theſe points, <hi>viz.</hi> Some have, and do hold the Deity to be ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitary. Some circumſcribed of the later Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was our late King <hi>JAMES,</hi> renowned for learning and depth of Judgement. Some have and do judge the Deity to conſiſt of a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170139:30"/>threefold perſonality. Others have and do hold Chriſt and the Holy Choſt to be creatures, and Gods only by deputation. Concerning the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God, ſome have and do hold the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of mankind and devils to be deſigned to everlaſting damnation. Some have and do hold and believe the contrary. Some conceive that all mankind may be ſaved if they will. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have and do believe, that not only they, but the Devils at the laſt day ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo, as by fire. Concerning the ordering and governing of the world, ſome will have it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by God, whom they ſay is preſent in all places and doth all things as himſelf will, not allowing any thing to be contingent, but that all things whatſoever, even the moſt inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, yea, and the moſt wicked, to be wrought by him; affirming, That wicked men do commit their Wickedneſs by the juſt impulſe of God: That the Devil and wicked men cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor contrive, nor execute any miſchief, nor ſo much as endeavour its execution any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then God himſelf doth command them; and they are compelled to perform obedience to ſuch commands. That Adultery or Murther, in as much as it is the Work of God, the author, mover, and compellor, it is not a crime; but in as much as it is of man, it is a wickedneſs; and ſo making God the predeterminer of all events, whether holy, or unholy; clean, or unclean; good or evil. Some aſcribe only good actions to God, and to his good Angels. Others aſſign all to men, becauſe they ſhall be judged according to their Works, which they conceive cannot
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170139:31"/>be reputed theirs if they were not free and voluntary agents in the doing of them. Some wil have all evil actions to be done by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Some judge him to have ſole command of this world, becauſe he is called the God of this world, and Prince of the Air. Concerning the perſon of Chriſt, ſome have judged it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted of two natures; ſome only of one, which ſome have holden to be Divine only. others hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. Concerning the death of Chriſt, ſome have; and do reſtrain it only to the Elect; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have, and do extend it to all mankind; and ſome to all creatures, or the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Concerning the nature of his death, ſome thought all mens ſins to be diſcharged thereby; ſome the ſins of the Elect only; and that Faith ſerves only to reveal this to them, and to give them comfort in it. Some conceive no mans ſins to be pardoned by his death, but that it ſerved only to confirm the truth of his Doctrine, namely, Remiſſion of ſins, &amp; ſalvation through an endeavour'd conformity to his life and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
            <p>And according to this diverſity of Opinions of God and Chriſt, are the diverſity of definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Faith, and the end and uſe of it, which ſome conceive to be Juſtification, others only Sanctification, and ſome both: No leſs vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are they in their Doctrine concerning Faith how it is obtained, which ſome hold to be by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; others, that it is acquired ſo concerning perſeverance in Faith. Concerning our Eſtate by birth, whether damnable or not. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacraments, and wherefore they ſerve.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170139:31"/>Concerning the perſons that are to adminiſter them. The perſons whom they are to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to, and when, and upon what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Concerning the Sabbath-day, whether mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, divine; or humane; when it beginneth, when it endeth, and what works may, or may not be done upon it. In all theſe, and ſundry others, even concerning Marriage, we find them no leſs divided then in thoſe before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Moreover there are many of great learning, who affirm Remiſſion of ſin to be a fruit or conſequence only, and no part of our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Many there are on the other ſide, who make Remiſſion of ſin antecedent to Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Juſtification to be its immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. Many take Remiſſion of ſin to be the whole of our Juſtification; yea, What large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes and Treatiſes are written very much to prove this, and many famous men for learning there are that maintain it. Many there be that take Juſtification to conſiſt partly in Remiſſion of ſin, and partly in the imputation of Chriſts own Righteouſneſs; and theſe, with the former, ſay, That accepting us as Righteous, is a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of Juſtification. Sin muſt firſt be remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (ſay the former) and Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imputed ours (ſay the later) before God can accept any man as righteous.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe are they at variance both how, and when Juſtification is obtained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How; whether it be by the active or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive obedience of Chriſt, or both; ſome ſay one way, ſome another; ſome ſay it is by Faith as it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170139:32"/>is an act; others, as it is an <hi>habet;</hi> and ſome ſay it is by Works.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When it is obtained: Some ſay it was from eternity by an eminent act of God; and that all the ſins of the Elect were actually pardoned; the Debt-book croſſed; the Hand-writing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that this grand Tranſaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the Mediator Jeſus Chriſt was concluded on, and diſpatcht long before men had any being in Nature or Grace. Some ſay it was only from the death of Chriſt; and ſome others ſay it is not until we actually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>Infinite are the differences even between men of greateſt eminency, and of moſt exquiſite learning and parts, as well about the definition of Faith, Repentance, and almoſt all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as about the moſt ſubſtantial and higheſt points in Divinity and of the Goſpel, as may be further ſeen in Mr. <hi>Blakes</hi> Exceptions, Mr. <hi>G. Kendals</hi> Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Joh. Goodwin;</hi> Mr. <hi>Ayre's</hi> Juſtification of Infidels; Mr. <hi>Joh. Craudons Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>R. Baxters</hi> Anſwers and Replyes to all theſe.</p>
            <p>And from whence can it be imagined that all theſe variety and contrariant Faiths and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do come, but from the variety, uncertainty, and inſufficiency of the Scripture clearly to reſolve theſe Points, and vindicate them from all ſuch Exceptions as lie againſt them on each hand; but the Scripture is ſo far from doing this, that each various and contrary Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is ſtifly upheld and maintained from the various Copies and Tranſlations thereof, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170139:32"/>from the various and contrary readings and meanings which each Opinioniſt reſpectively may and doth put upon the Scripture it ſelf, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that indeed it is now made capable of any impreſſion which every learned and witty man can invent and pleaſeth to put upon it to ſerve his own turn and occaſion, though he face about and change never ſo much, never ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And thus each man ſtill makes the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be like to Pictures, wherein every man in the Room believes they look on him only, and that whereſoever he ſtandeth, or how often ſoever he changeth his ſtation.</p>
            <p>Now whether all this doth ariſe from a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral hidden ſenſe of the Scripture or from the brevity of them, or for want of many Books mentioned in Scripture, whereof we never had either Original or Copy; or from miſtakes made by Tranſcribers, Printers, or Tranſlators; or from the varions acceptation of words and phraſes contained in them; and in probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, underſtandable only by ſuch perſons to whom they were firſt written, who being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand grounded in the Faith and Principles of Chriſtianity, and inſtrueted in the things treated upon, were thereby enabled aright to underſtand the mind of the Pen-men in what they did but briefly touch upon, in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to them: Or whether from all of theſe, or from any other cauſe or cauſes, I leave to the wiſe and conſiderate to determine; but certainly were they perſpicuous in their ſenſe, ſo many learned, ſtudious, good men could not poſſible
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170139:33"/>ſo much have erred and been divided in their underſtanding of them. And if ſuch as theſe, notwithſtanding all their advantages of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have not been able to reſolve the truth of theſe Doctrines ſo familiarly mentioned in the Scripture, and ſo neceſſarily required to true Chriſtianity, who ſhall conceive that they were intended by God for the ground of Faith and Worſhip for all, or any ſort of men whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, except we ſhall conceive that the unlearned ſort of men are in a better capacity perfectly to reſolve the ſenſe of Scripture then the learned, which is too groſs to imagine; or elſe that all men are bound to know and conform their Faith and Worſhip to a Doctrine that none of them certainly underſtand, which none will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, it being inconſiſtent with that Juſtice and Goodneſs which all confeſſe to be in Almighty God.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee what to this point is ſaid by learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> in his forecited Book, pag. 13. his words are theſe, <hi>viz. It is a demonſtration that nothing can be neceſſary to be believed upon pain of damnation but ſuch propoſitions of which it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that God hath ſpoken and taught them to us, and of which it is certaine that this is their ſenſe and purpoſe: for if the ſenſe be uncertaine, we can no more be obliged to believe it in a certaine ſenſe, then we are to believe it at all if it were not certaine that God delivered it; but if it be only certaine that God ſpake it and not certaine to what ſenſe; our faith of it is to be as indeterminate as its ſenſe, nor is it conſonant to Gods juſtice to believe of him that he can or will require more.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170139:33"/>
            <p>But to go on, and bring this neater; It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt (even in thoſe Scriptures we have) that Jeſus Chriſt requires no credit to be given to his Doctrine, either upon his own bare word, or the bare word of any perſons whatſoever (as before is ſet forth) <hi>If I bear witneſs of my ſelf</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my witneſs is not true; neither receive I teſtimony of men; the works that I do in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Name, they bear witneſs of me that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſent me.</hi> And when he is blaming the Scribes and Phariſees for their unbelief in him, he thus far excuſeth them in it, <hi>That if he had not done among them the Works that none other man did, they had not had ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who can conceive that Chriſt ſhould pronounce men guiltleſs for not believing him upon his own bare teſtimony, and yet not hold men much more guiltleſs for not believing the Scripture upon its bare teſtimony. Chriſt, though he bare witneſs of himſelf, his witneſs was certain and true: whereas Copies and Tranſlations, as before we have ſeen, are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and erroneous; Chriſt diſclaims the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of men, yea of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, as a ground inſufficient to engage men to believe in his Doctrine, though all that <hi>John</hi> ſaid of him was true; and what he had heard and ſeen, that he teſtified. And ſhall we imagine that he will binde all the ſucceeding generations of men to believe the truth of Chriſt and the Goſpel upon any ſuch inferior teſtimony as the teſtimony only of ſuch as diſclaim infallibility, and have neither heard nor ſeen as <hi>John</hi> did. Shall God and Chriſt be true, and all men lyars? and yet
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170139:34"/>ſhall fallible men be preferred before them, in being believed upon lower &amp; eaſier terms then either they, or their moſt infallible ſervants? Or ſhal God be conceived to require contraries of men, as not to believe ſuper-natural truths (ſuch the Goſpel is judged to be) without a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table evidence? and on the other ſide, require men to believe it without any ſuch evidence: Shall men be blameleſs, and blamed by him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one and the ſame account? If this cannot be, as ſurely it cannot, then it muſt neceſſarily follow, That the Scripture was never inſtituted or intended by Almighty God to be the ground of Chriſtian Faith and Religion, or to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in, and obeyed by mankind to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Moreover it is evident, if we may take the meaning according to the ſenſe of the words, as they are delivered to us in Tranſlations; That the Epiſtles, and St. <hi>Johns Revelation</hi> in the New Teſtament were all written unto Believers; and that both the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to <hi>Theophilus,</hi> an inſtructed Diſciple, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. And it is moſt probable, that the other three Goſpels were written to believers alſo, at leaſt, for their ſakes, eſpecially for ſuch of them as did not ſee Chriſt themſelves after his reſurrection, whereby he mightily declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Son of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. whereof the reſt of the Apoſtles, as well as <hi>Thomas,</hi> much doubted whileſt he lay dead, as may appear by 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. where St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf and of the reſt, ſaith, <hi>That God of his abundant mercy had begotten them again to a lively hope by</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170139:34"/>the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, and what may be underſtood by this, but that all their hope was extinct, or languiſhed by his death, and revived again by his reſurrection? And that his being riſen from death was very hardly believed by any of them, may appear from <hi>Mark</hi> 16.10, 11. when <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> told the Diſciples, as they were mourning and weeping, that Chriſt was alive, and that ſhe had ſeen him, they believed it not, and from <hi>Luke</hi> 24.21, 22. where two of the Diſciples, after they had with much ſadneſs declared how the chief Prieſts and Rulers had delivered Chriſt to be condemned to death, and had crucified him, (ſaid) we truſted that it had been he which ſhould have redeemed Iſrael, intimating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that he being then dead and gone they were quite hopeleſs, expecting nothing leſs then his riſing again; for after, when they heard by the women that he was alive, they were aſtoniſhed at it, &amp; in <hi>Mark</hi> 16.13. when upon his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto two of them theſe went and told it to the reſt of the Apoſtles, yet they believed it not, and hence it was, that he appeared and ſhewed himſelf to his Diſciples, 500 at once, and familiarly and often to ſuch of them, as he intended to make his Apoſtles and chief witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the world, to confirm this their belief in his reſurrection, inſomuch that when he firſt appeared to them, he ſhewed them his hands and his feet, and bad them handle and ſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.39. <hi>Jeh.</hi> 20.20, &amp;c. where it is very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that <hi>Thomas</hi> not being then preſent, would not believe the report of all the reſt of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170139:35"/>Apoſtles that he was riſen, unleſs he might ſee and handle his wounds alſo as they had done, wherein alſo afterward Chriſt gave him ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, by permitting him to do ſo likewiſe, and then withal left a bleſſing in the hands of the Apoſtles for all ſuch other of his Diſciples who had not ſeen him (as they had done) yet did believe his reſurrection. Wherefore moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite it was, That as well for the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this bleſſing, as for the confirmation of the Diſciples &amp; believers in the belief of Chriſts reſurrection, they ſhould write the Narratives of all theſe things, and moſt probable it is, the Apoſtles did therefore write the three other Goſpels, for theſe ends and purpoſes as may be gathered by comparing <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle with the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> (that is) <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. with 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p>I have been the larger upon this, becauſe I finde not only ordinary men, but moſt learned profound Teachers do pervert this place of Scripture to the miſ-leading of many (whether ignorantly or purpoſely I will not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.)</p>
            <p n="1">1 In making the ſence of the words, as if Chriſt thereby did intend a bleſſing on all ſuch, as in the future ſhould believe the teachings of men without ſeeing any divine evidence to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the truth of their Doctrine: whereas Chriſts words had reſpect onely to ſuch other of his Diſciples or believers, who had not ſeen Chriſt as <hi>Thomas</hi> did, yet did believe his being riſen again, which <hi>Thomas</hi> by no means would do, until he had both ſeen and felt him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170139:35"/>2 In making the Apoſtles words in verſ. 31. to be intended to all the world as a ground ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for true and ſaving faith, whereas if it were ſo, it might ſerve inſtead of a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in all nations, when as to the generality of mankinde it was meer barbariſm coming from the Apoſtle but in one language onely, which would have been a failer, not imaginable in the Apoſtle, having the guift of tongues enabling him purpoſely to teach all nations &amp; people in their reſpective languages, and accordingly no doubt he would have written, if he had intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it for any ſuch great and general uſe, but it is moſt plain, that his intention therein was onely to confirm believers of that one language in their belief of that one great article of Chriſts being the Son of God whereof they could not doubt, if they firmly believed his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And if we may have leave to give a like cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the Scripture in this matter and to make concluſions from plain premiſſes, ſuch as many would have us give and make from none at all, or at beſt, from ſuch as are far more dark; We may both ſee and conclude, that the Scripture is ſo far from teſtifying it ſelf to be any ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground for faith and conviction to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing world, that it teſtifies the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In that it teſtifies, that the power of God by ſignes and miracles accompanying the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and atteſting the truth and divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their doctrine was the onely true ground of faith and conviction unto unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170139:36"/>as before is ſet forth, and is evident by theſe texts, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.7, 8, 9. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 8. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.18, 19, 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.6. And that thus, and upon this foundation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets, the true Miniſtry of the Goſpel fitted by gifts, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.8, 11, 12, 13. Chriſt Jeſus himſelf being the chief Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, was Chriſtian belief, and Churches foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. And that no foundation other then ſuch, can any man warrantably lay or plead for, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that it teſtifies, That whatſoever is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in any unknown tongue, or but in a doubtful and uncertain ſence, is as barbariſm, not obliging any to believe it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.7, 8, 9, 10. for no man is bound, or can infallibly and convincingly believe any thing which is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly and convincingly revealed to him.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all the uncertainties afore ſpecified, yet how doth each Sect of Chriſtians aſſert, that they are of the true belief, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny therefore challenge the higheſt priviledges of true believers, mentioned in Scripture to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto them, yea, and ſome ſuch do they aſſume to have, as no true believer ever had in this life, I ſhall give inſtances. They aſſume to be true believers, and to have the Spirit of God, yea the ſame, as true believers formerly had, and by which the Scripture was given forth. To be actually juſtified, to have eternal life, and to be already paſſed from death to life. To have Chriſt, and his divine nature within them, and that white ſtone wherein a new is written,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170139:36"/>which no man knoweth, ſaving he that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherein if I am not exceedingly miſtaken, they are, firſt in their conceiving themſelves to be true believers, yet ground it upon various, yea on contrary doctrines, and want both the true ground upon which true believers built their faith and the ſame power whereby true believers were to be known, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17, 18. or that they have the ſame ſpirit by which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture was given forth, and yet make uſe of, and cite texts amiſs rendered in tranſlations, even as others do, who pretend not to have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what can reaſonably be imagined or underſtood by believers being juſtified by faith, I am inclined to think it is no more then their being ſaved by hope, and what is or can be meant by this more then now in this life to hope to be ſaved hereafter in the life to come, as the Apoſtle reaſoneth, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.24, 25. where ſpeaking of himſelf and other believers (ſaith) we are ſaved by hope, but hope that is ſeen is not hope, for what a man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for, for if we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with patience wait for it, and why may not the ſame be ſaid of being juſtified by faith, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being likewiſe the evidence of things not ſeen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. which when they once come to be ſeen (or actually to be injoyed) then faith as well as hope (in reſpect of thoſe things believed and hoped for) ſhall ceaſe, for what need a man either to hope or truſt any longer for that, of which he hath already
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170139:37"/>the ſight or actual poſſeſſion, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>The like may be underſtood at leaſt, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, of theſe and the like texts. He that hath everlaſting life is already paſſed from death to life, muſt not the meaning be? That he believes in this, that he ſhall actually enjoy everlaſting life in the world to come, and at the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even that everlaſting life, which he hath here onely by faith, unleſs it can reaſonably be imagined, that every believer muſt have actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally two everlaſting lives; one here in this world, and the other in the world to come, to commence not until the reſurrection. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was ſaid of believers, That Chriſt was in them, this was by faith likewiſe; and where it was told them, that they were partakers of the divine nature it was there alſo told them, that it was by having promiſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. which they laid hold on by faith and to be actual partakers of the divine nature at the reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47.48.</p>
            <p>And for the white ſtone that is likewiſe to be received in the life to come actually, even at the ſame time when believers ſhall receive power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Nations, &amp;c. which will not be until the reſurrection, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.17, 26, 27. <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4.</p>
            <p>How ſottiſh therefore is the practice of all ſuch as attribute any divine eſteem, honour, or worſhip to any man, conceiving him from theſe and the like texts to have Chriſt, or the divine nature in him, or to be ſent of God, to have the Spirit of God, or to have divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170139:37"/>not bringing with him divine power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently to atteſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſince there are ſuch various and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory opinions, even among men of eminent learning; parts, and integrity, as before is ſeen about juſtification, wherein its more probable that all have erred, then poſſible all to be in the truth. I have alſo propoſed my opinion, though different from all theirs, declaring what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive may be meant by believers, being juſtified by faith, comparing it to, and expounding it by the phraſe of the Apoſtle, we are ſaved by hope, and by ſome other texts of like import, as, He that believeth hath everlaſting life, and is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſſed from death to life; and I think that no text can be found more poſitive for preſent and actual juſtification of a believer in this life, then theſe and ſome other texts are for his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſalvation and glorification here alſo; as namely, He hath tranſlated us into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his dear ſon, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly place in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. but ye are come to Mount Sion, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. And now without offence to any let me here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this point my thoughts alittle further, not impoſing any thing upon any man but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all men to that freedome, from which no man can juſtly take them. Thus whether that actual juſtification and ſalvation of men, come not both together, and neither to be untill the day of judgement; and that faith or believing ſimply conſidered will not then ſave any man:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170139:38"/>How then can it now juſtifie or make any man at any time the more acceptable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>To make that which is here intended plain to be underſtood, we need diſtinguiſh of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving:</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a believing a thing to be true, which is the proper act of the underſtanding; this I call a believing ſimply conſidered. Thus to believe (not being in a mans choice, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon him by force of the evidence that is brought to evince it) procures no reward or acceptance with God, and the not believing in the ſame ſence procures no puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There is obeying or diſobeying of that truth ſo believed, which being an act of the will, and in a mans choice procures reward or puniſhment. This alſo is called a believing, or a not believing, and in ſome places a hearing, or a not hearing, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8, 9. it's called a not-believing, and in <hi>Act</hi> 3.22, 23. it's called a hearing and a not hearing; and when or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever eternal life or ſalvation was promiſed upon believing or hearing, or puniſhment threatened upon not believing or not hearing, there alwayes obeying or diſobeying is implied, though not expreſt. And herein let appeal be made to any rational and impartial man, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Jews, who onely believed Chriſt to be the true Meſſiah, or the Goſpel to be truth, without obeying him or it, ſhould have been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereby; when as we find that ſalvation and damnation at the laſt day, to be diſpoſed onely according to obedience and diſobedience,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170139:38"/>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. to the end.</p>
            <p>Herewith judicious Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> concurs, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the very ſame, in ſence, though different in expreſſion. In his fore-cited Book, <hi>pag</hi> 24, 25. his words being as followeth. Faith (ſaith he) if it be taken for an act of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meerly, it is ſo far from being that excellent grace that juſtifies us, that it is not good at all, but <hi>in genere naturae,</hi> and makes the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better in it ſelf, or pleaſing to God, juſt as ſtrength doth the arm, or beauty the face, or health the body; theſe are natural perfections indeed, and ſo knowledge or true belief is to the underſtanding, but this makes us not at all more acceptable to God, for then the unlearned were certainly in a damnable condition; and all good Scholars ſhould be ſaved, (whereas I am afraid too much of the contrary is true) but unleſs faith be made moral by mixture of choice and charity, it is nothing but a natural perfection, not a grace or a vertue, and this is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proved in this, that by the confeſſion of all men, of all intereſts and perſwaſions, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meer belief, invincible ignorance is our excuſe, if we be deceived, which could not be, but that neither to believe aright is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor to believe amiſs is reprovable, but where both one and the other is voluntary, and choſen antecedently or conſequently, by prime election, or <hi>ex post facto,</hi> and ſo comes to be conſidered in morality, and it is part of a good life, or a bad life reſpectively.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall ſay otherwiſe, it is to ſay,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170139:39"/>that ſome men ſhall be damned, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help it, periſh without their own fault, and be miſerable for ever, becauſe of their unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to be deceived thorow their own ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and natural, or accidental but inculpable infirmity; for it is inconſiſtant with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, to condemn thoſe who erre, where errour hath nothing of the will in it, who therefore cannot repent of their errour, becauſe they believe it true, who therefore cannot make compenſation, becauſe they know not that they are tied to dereliction of it, thus far the Doctor.</p>
            <p>In the firſt ſence <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with his Egyptian Magicians, believed, that the miracles which <hi>Moſes</hi> did was by the finger of God, to which belief or convincement they were not Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, but compelled by force of the ſaid mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles wrought in their ſighs, yet they diſobeying the meſſage confirmed ſo by thoſe miracles were deſtroyed, notwithſtand their ſo belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>In this ſence alſo it is ſaid, <hi>Joh</hi> 12 42, 43. That many of the chief Rulers believed in Chriſt, but did not confeſs him, becauſe of the Phariſees, leſt they ſhould be turned out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, becauſe they loved the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>Hereunto compare, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7, 8, 9. where Chriſt ſets forth the ends of his ſending the ſpirit or power, by which the Apoſtles &amp; others wrought ſuch mighty works, one whereof was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of ſin, where note the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170139:39"/>when he comes (ſaies Chriſt) he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of ſin, As if he had ſaid, That when or whereſoever this ſpirit and power which I will ſend you ſhall demonſtate it ſelf in the world to the ſons and drughters of men, it ſhall certainly procure the convincement of their underſtandings to believe the truth of the Goſpel atteſted thereby; And why of ſin? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they believe not (that is) obey not the Goſpel in their wills and affections being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced (or believing) of the truth thereof in their underſtandings.</p>
            <p>For further juſtifying this Expoſition, take notice, That, that which in the former text is termed a belief, is here in this later text ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a convincement and both having reference to the underſtanding. And in like manner, that which in the former text is termed a not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, is in this later text termed a not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and both having reference to the will and affections; in reſpect of obedience, ſo that in the Scripture-ſence a man at one and the ſame time may be ſaid to believe, and not to believe, (that is) to believe intellectually, and not to believe obediencially, whereby he becomes a ſelf-condemner, being found guilty even by the verdict of his own underſtanding and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>This being that great condemnation, which in <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.17. is ſet forth with an Emphaſis on men for loving darkneſs rather then light, which no man can reaſonably be ſaid to do, unleſs he ſeeth the light; for how can any man be ſaid to love one thing rather then another,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170139:40"/>which he never ſaw. Adde to this 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of ſome that periſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved. This they could not juſtly be blamed for, unleſs they had apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it in their underſtandings to be a truth; For whatſoever in my underſtanding I judge an untruth, (though the ſame in it ſelf be a truth, yet whiles I do judge it otherwiſe) I neither can or ought to love it as a truth.</p>
            <p>Hereunto alſo contributes the parable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by Chriſt, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.) of a King who at the marriage of his ſon, made a great feaſt, and bad many thereto; and when all things were in readineſs he ſent for his gueſts, who (although all were unwilling to come, yet) not one of them ſaid, or could ſay, That he did not know of the Kings invitation, or that he did not believe the truth of the meſſage, or of the great preparation made for his bountiful entertainment and welcome, none of all which was doubted by them, nor did any of them ſay, that between them and the Kings Palace was any gulf or ſea, mountain, or rock, exceeding their power to get over, or that any one of them were either ſick, or lame or otherwiſe diſabled to come, but their meer wills and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions adhering to the things of this life was the onely impediment, and all their excuſe.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And for that which may be objected from</hi> John 12.37. <hi>Though Chriſt had done ſo many miracles before the Jews, yet they believe not on him, but ſaid; He caſt out Devils by the Prince of Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170139:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may be anſwered, That though they believed not ſo as to love or obey him, yet they believed (as the chief Rulers afore-mentioned did) being convinced in their underſtandings by the mighty works done by Chriſt among them: for how elſe could their meer ſaying ſo amount to any ſin, much leſs to the unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, wherewith they were charged by Chriſt, if they had but ſpoken in the ſimplicity of their hearts, and as in truth they apprehended &amp; believed; for it is of none but ſuch, that Chriſt ſpeaks in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.24. where he ſayes, If I had not done among them the works which no other man did, they had not had ſin, but now have they both ſeen and hated both me and my father. Where note, 1. What the great works done among them produced; namely, their ſeeing, convincement, or believing intellectually. 2. What the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of that their ſeeing was; (namely) their hating both him and his father, from whence ſprang this their ſaying, which aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated their ſin, which had had nobeginning, or being unleſs they had ſeen and been convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>And therefore I conceive from the premiſſes may be ſafely concluded, That none at years of diſcretion, in whoſe ſight and preſence ſignes and miracles were wrought by Chriſt, or his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Miniſters to atteſt the truth and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority of their doctrine, but they were ſo convinced, as to believe the ſame to be true, and of God; or thus; That all unbelievers
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170139:41"/>(ſeeing the great witneſs by ſigns and miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which God gave to their doctrine) were ſo convinced in their underſtandings, as they could not but rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude and believe the ſame to be true, and of god.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all that's premiſed, and all the late and great pretences of Reformation, yet the pretence of divine right ſtill remains, and is challenged by many without divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or manifeſtation, for (beſides the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal, or rather Papal relicks of ordination, that is, ſtill retained and upheld amongſt us to be of divine right) did not the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (ſo called) conſiſting of Independents as well as of Presbiterians, hold themſelves and their Aſſembly to be divinely authorized from the meer recital of the Apoſtles and Elders aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling at Jeruſalem, mentioned in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. And as theſe ſtill maintained their authority to be divine, which was by holy Orders (as they call it) conferred upon them from the Biſhops ſuppoſed divine authority, lately exploded as Antichriſtian; So theſe (with the Separatiſts) do ſtill maintain the baptizing of Infants, to be of divine right from the meer recital of the Covenant of Circumciſion made with <hi>Abruham</hi> and his natural ſeed, wherein <hi>Abraham</hi> was commanded to circumcize all his male-ſervants, whether born in his houſe, or bought with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of any ſtranger, though not of his ſeed, as well as his natural ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. but theſe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize no ſervant from that ground, which they may as warrantably do as baptize any Infant.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170139:41"/>
            <p>Nor are the Anabaptiſts (who deny the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Infants) excuſable upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in pretending to derive divine authority to preach and baptize from the meer recital of that authority which was by Chriſt given per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to the eleven Apoſtles, who both recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and exerciſed the ſame long before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital thereof in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. from which no ſuch authority can be derived to any, becauſe on that recital no authority at all was conferred by the eleven Apoſtles themſelves there mentioned, nor was their authority the more for it's being there recited; nor had it been the leſs, if it had never been recited, either there or any where elſe, and therefore no ſuch authority can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from that or any other Text.</p>
            <p>Beſides, theſe are very partial, in that they aſſume ſuch great and ſublime authority to themſelves, from the meer recital of ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and not withall judge themſelves alſo, as well bound by the recital of that prohibition given alſo by Chriſt to the ſame Apoſtles, <hi>(viz.) That they ſhould not go out in the excerciſe of that Miniſterial Function, until they were indued with power from on high, by the coming down of the Holy Ghoſt upon them, Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4.8. And therefore upon due conſideration of the whole matter it will be found. That theſe do aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (from meer recitals) more authority then that which Chriſt gave to the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and whereof the Scriptures are but bare recitals.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170139:42"/>
            <p>Some other there are, who diſowning all the former wayes of conveyance yet to keep on foot that divine authority, and that reverence &amp; accommodation which uſually they received thereby in the world, would by another trick both cozen themſelves and all others (their own conſciences only excepted) by telling the people that this divine authority (which hitherto they have miſt of) muſt needs be in them; and that they by their free election and bountiful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution may convey it on whom they will, and on them if they pleaſe; but this alſo will be found a meer ſhuffle and as vain as any of the former; for we finde both by Scripture and reaſon; That a true Miniſtry divinely autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed and impowered, did and alwayes muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, beget, and conſtitute a true Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely authoriſed; and that no Church or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whatſoever, who are not ſo begotten and indued with divine power and authority them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, can poſſibly convey any ſuch divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority on any other: this is evidently ſeen a truth by all the empty, vain, and fruitleſs lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, uſed as well in particular Churches, as by others in their Ordination of Miniſters, in imitation of the Apoſtles laying on their hands whereby the manifeſt and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful gifts of the Spirit (as that of tongues and propheſie, &amp;c.) were conveyed, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6.</p>
            <p>This form is ſtill retained generally through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſtendome, as well as amongſt us; but where's the power that ſhould follow? here's
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170139:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſhell, but where's the kernel? Might not little children or Apes, in imitation of theſe, lay hands one upon one another, to as good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and with as much ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Nor want we many amongſt us, who would needs have this whole Nation governed meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Lawes and Ordinances of the Jews recited in Scripture, and by Scriptural precepts onely, pretending its divine authority to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like over us, as the Lawes and Ordinances given by <hi>Moſes</hi> were over the Jews; but how by this our caſe would be better then now it is (I cannot imagine) unleſs our Lawyers could (which is not likely) and would againſt their own profit (which is not to be hoped) make more certain and undoubted Tranſlations, Commentaries, and Expoſitions of Scripture, then ever any of the moſt Orthodox Divines have hitherto done.</p>
            <p>But theſe men (as it ſeems) deeming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Saints, and to be divinely authorized from Scripture, to make this Nation the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, (and to ſet up, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thronize themſelves, to rule and raign for Chriſt, and in his ſtead) do declare it now their duty to effect all this by force and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In their Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard ſet up,</hi> pag. 10.</note> inviting all the upright in heart to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and joyn with them in this the work of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170139:43"/>Lord,
<note n="*" place="margin">I wiſh that all Chriſtians, beſides ſuch as do jump with them, were not to be numbred among the Heathen, upon whom they would execute vengeane if they had power in their hands to do it.</note> 
               <hi>To execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon he Heathen, and puniſhment upon the people, &amp;c.</hi> and for this take their warrant from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.15. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 149.7. applying theſe and very many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures of like import now unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which do properly belong to other times &amp; perſons, and not to be fulfilled until the times of reſtoration of the Jews, and the perſonal coming of Chriſt to ſet up his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>But theſe miſtakes (at leaſt as I conceive) do ariſe from their deeming (as many others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately do) that the coming of Chriſt and his Kingdome is to be meerly ſpiritual by his grace coming and ruling in mens hearts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his perſonal coming, whereas the Scripture plainly ſets forth his perſonal coming in power and great glory viſible to all men, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 3 20, 21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.27. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 40.5. after which he will gather together his ancient and elect people the Jews out of all Countreys where they are diſperſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.31. compared with <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.12, &amp;c. after which he will ſet up his Kingdome, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.30, 31. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.11, 12, 13. which ſhall be upon the earth, and at the end of this world, when he will gather and deſtroy out of his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170139:43"/>Kingdome (the earth) all the wicked, and them that work iniquity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.39, 40, 41. Then (and not till then) ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdome of ther fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. and then Chriſt will be King over all the earth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.9. which will not be until his perſonal coming on the earth, as <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5. do manifeſt. And then will be fulfilled the promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his ſeed to inherit the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for an everlaſting poſſeſſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8. wherein whileſt he lived he did but ſo journ and dwell as in a ſtrange Countrey, with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> heirs with him of the ſame promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8, 9. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.4, 5. theſe all died in faith and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of that promiſe nevertheleſs to be performed to them afterward, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.13. Then will the Kingdomes of this world become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and his Chriſt, wherein he ſhall reign for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11, 15. having the Heathen for his inheritance, and the utter parts of the earth for his poſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28. And then alſo will be fulfilled that promiſe to the righteous and meek, to inherit the earth for ever, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.9, 11, 18, 29. although in the mean time, in this life they lie under all oppreſſion and tyranny of wicked men, at whom the Lord laugheth, for he ſeeth that his day is comming, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. even the ſame Lords day, wherein Saint <hi>John</hi> was in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, heard a great voice behind him like a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and ſaw Chriſt being come in glory, talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.10. to 20. and after ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in viſion the great tranſactions and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170139:44"/>which Chriſt at his coming will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally make upon the earth, as that all the tribes of Iſrael were
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The marking their houſes with the blood of the paſſeover, whereby to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt them from hurt by the plagues &amp; judgments then to be poured out on their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies the Egyptians, was a lively type,</hi> Exod. 12.12. <hi>which judgments may be counted but as flea-bitings in compariſon of thoſe that ſhall be poured out upon the world at their great and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deliverance by Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </note> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, before liberty was given to hurt the earth, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.3. To preſerve them from being hurt by any of the great plagues then ready to be poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their enemies, &amp; the Antichriſtian world. The great overthrow of the beaſt, falſe prophet, and the Kings of the earth, with all their great and formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Armies, the fall of Babylon and deſtruction of the Whore. The Kingdomes of this world to become the Kingdomes of Chriſt. The new Jeruſalem to come down from God out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yea all things made new; as new heavens and new earth, which ſhall be ſo eſtabliſhed that it cannot be moved, <hi>Pſal</hi> 93.1.96.10. not being created in vain, but to be inhabited and remain world without end, when Iſrael the very ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall be gathered together out of all Nations, and be ſaved with an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſalvation, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45.17, 18, 19. and 60.20. yea, the Gentiles ſhall bring their ſons in their arms, and their daughters ſhall be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170139:44"/>carried upon their ſhoulders, <hi>Eſa</hi> 49.22. Then the earth ſhall yield her increaſe, and God, even their own God ſhall
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Gentiles have great cauſe to long and pray for this mercy and bleſſing upon the Jews from the Lord, that his way may be known upon earth, and his ſaving health among all nations,</hi> v. 1, 2. <hi>for then will the law go out of Sion, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem,</hi> Eſa. 2.3. <hi>and then peace ſhall be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to the end of the earth,</hi> Pſ. 46.9. <hi>not onely amongſt men, but among the beaſts of the field alſo,</hi> Eſa. 2.4. Eſa. 11.6. <hi>according to the Angels proclamation at the birth of Chriſt,</hi> Luke 2.14.</note> bleſs them, and all the ends of the earth ſhall fear him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.6, 7. Then ſhall a handful of corn be ſown upon the top of the mountains, the fruit whereof ſhall ſhake like <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> and they of the city ſhal flouriſh like graſs of the earth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 72.16. for then the Lord will make their wilderneſs like <hi>Eden,</hi> and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart like the garden of the Lord, joy and gladnesſhal befound therein, thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and the voice of melody, <hi>Eſay</hi> the 51.3. Then ſhall they eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their glory ſhall they boaſt themſelves, for their ſhame they ſhall have double, and for their confuſion they ſhall rejoyce in their portion, therefore in their own land they ſhall poſſeſs double, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy ſhall be unto them, <hi>Eſa</hi> 61.6, 7. And their ſeed ſhall be known among the Gentiles, and their off-ſpring among the people: All that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170139:45"/>ſee them ſhall acknowledge, that they are the ſeed which the Lord hath bleſſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9 and hence it will be, that ten men out of all langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the nations, ſhall take hold of the skirt of him, that is, a Jew, ſaying, We will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.23. And then alſo the Lord will be a great King, above all gods; in whoſe hands will be the deep places of the earth, and the ſtrength of the hills will be his alſo, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.3, 4. Then the Lord with righteouſneſs will judge the poor, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.4. The throne of iniquity ſhall then have no fellowſhip with him, which frameth miſchief by a law, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 94.20 for all the horns of the wicked ſhall be then cut off, and the horns of the righteous exalted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75 10. yea; the Lord will then utterly deſtroy, and caſt out all wicked and unrighteous oppreſſours and tyrants from off the face of the earth, even in the ſight of the righteous, to their everlaſting joy, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37 32. to 37. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17, 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.41. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 21.8; 9, 10.— whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the righteous will then ſay among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; Come, behold the works of the Lord, what deſolations he hath made upon the earth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 46.8.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall the Jews, and the ten tribes be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one Kingdome, and never more be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, be brought again into their own land, and dwell therein, both they and their children, and their childrens children for ever, <hi>Ezek</hi> 37 although immediately before this their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170139:45"/>they ſhall be in ſuch great affliction and dejection of ſpirit, that they ſhall in their own ſenſe account themſelves a loſt people, caſt off, and quite forſaken of the Lord, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope of deliverance; and this is moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly ſet forth under the ſimilitude of dry bones, and even as men quite dead and buried, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. but even then out of this great tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of theirs (which will be ſo great as there was never any the like upon any people ſince there was a nation upon the earth, no nor ever ſhall be) ſhall they be delivered and ſaved by Chriſt with an everlaſting ſalvation, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.21, 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1, 7, 8. And therefore it is (as I conceive) that thoroughout the Scripture are ſcattered ſuch eminent and emphatical expreſſions &amp; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning this people to ſupport them, and prevent their fainting in this day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble; as then bidding them to look up and lift up their heads with comfort, for then <hi>their redemption, reſtoration, &amp; the ſetting up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God will be nigh at hand,</hi> Luke 21.26, 27, 28, 30. And although many generations and nations ſhall periſh, and be forgotten from off the earth before that day come, yet their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or nation ſhall not paſs away, but be preſerved to ſee this great deliverance and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the whole houſe of Iſrael, according to the promiſes and oath of God to <hi>Abraham, Luke</hi> 1.68. <hi>to</hi> 76. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26, compared with <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.20, &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.32, 33. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.8, 9. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1, 8. And in <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170139:46"/>36. the Lord expreſſeth himſelf concerning this people thus, <hi>In my jealouſie, in the fire of my jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and in my fury, becauſe ye have born the ſhame of the Heathen; He would therefore take them from among the Heathen, and gather them out of all Countreys, and bring them into their own land, would build their ruined places, He the Lord had ſpoken it, and would perform it,</hi> v. 5, 6.24, 36. and in Ezek. 37. <hi>O my people come out of your graves:</hi> and again, <hi>O my people, &amp;c.</hi> And in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa. 41.9, 10. <hi>Thou art my ſervant, I have choſen thee, and will not caſt thee away, fear not, I am with thee, be not diſmayed, for I will help thee, yea I wil uphold thee with the right hand of my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> and v. 13, 14. <hi>I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, ſaying unto thee, Fear not, I will help thee, fear not thou worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>ye men of Iſrael, I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, and thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, the holy one of Iſrael:</hi> and in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.14, 15, 16. where Sion ſaid, <hi>The Lord hath forſaken me, and my God hath forgotten me:</hi> (It's anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking childe, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb, yea, they may forget, yet will not I forget thee; Behold I have graven thee upon the palmes of my hands,</hi> &amp;c. And in <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Fear thou not, O my ſervant</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſaith the Lord, neither be diſmayed, O Iſrael: for lo, I will ſave thee from afar, and thy ſeed from the land of their captivity, and</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall return, and ſhall be in reſt, and he quiet, and none ſhall make him afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe with many promiſes more of like ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170139:46"/>(for the comfort and ſupport of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the natural ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi>) are ſcattered throughout the Scripture.</p>
            <p>And that after their deliverance out of this their great trouble, <hi>They will become the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt people and Nation upon the earth,</hi> Mich. 4:1, 6, 7, 8: it being ſaid of theſe, <hi>That they ſhall be among the Gentiles, as a lion among the flocks of ſheep, who if he go thorow, both treadeth down and teareth in pieces, and none can deliver, and all their enemies ſhall be cut off,</hi> Mich. 5:8, 9:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe ſhall be like a harth of fire among wood, and like a torch of fire in a ſheaf, and ſhall devour all the people round about on the right hand, and on the left,</hi> Zach: 12:6:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe ſhall be as the Lords battel, Axe and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of war, wherewith he will break in pieces the Nations, and deſtroy the Kingdomes,</hi> Jerem. 51:20:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they whoſe horns ſhall be made Iron, and hooſs braſs, to break in pieces many people, whoſe gain and ſubſtance ſhall be conſecrated to the Lord of the whole earth,</hi> Mich. 4.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they that ſhall be as a fire and flame to the houſe of</hi> Eſau, <hi>to devour them, for the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it,</hi> Obed. 18: And then will be verified the Word of the Lord to <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> which he told her, <hi>That two Nations were in her womb, and that the elder ſhould ſerve the younger,</hi> Gen. 25:23: <hi>which is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the two perſons</hi> Eſau <hi>&amp;</hi> Jacob, as ſome unadviſedly do imagine: for <hi>Eſau</hi> never in perſon ſerved nor worſhipped <hi>Jacob,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170139:47"/>did <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 33:3, 13, 15. but this was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie concerning their poſterities, and to be fulfilled at the time of the Jews exaltation and power, ſet forth by theſe Texts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they that ſhall be made a new ſharp threſhing Inſtrument, having teeth, wherewith the Lord will threſh the mountains, beat them ſmall, and make the hills as chaffe,</hi> Eſay 41.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they to whom ſhall be reſtored Judges, as at firſt; and Counſellors, as at the beginning, and whoſe officers ſhall be peace, and whoſe exactors righteouſneſs.</hi> Eſa. 1.26. and 60.17:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they on whom the glory of the Lord will ariſe, and ſo ſhine, that the Gentiles may come to their light, and Kings to the brightneſs of their riſing, ſo that the abundance of the Sea ſhall be converted to them, and the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto them,</hi> Eſa. 60:1. to 7:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they, of whom a little one ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a thouſand, and a ſmall one a ſtrong Nation,</hi> Eſa: 60:22:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they to whom Kings shall be their nurſing fathers, and Queens shall be their Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and shall bowe their faces to the earth, and lick the duſt of their feet,</hi> Eſa. 49:23:</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170139:47"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they of whom</hi> Balaam <hi>propheſied, That they ſhould have the ſtrength of a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn, to eat up the Nations, their enemies, break their bones, and pierce them thorow with arrows, and lie down as a lion, and as a ſtrong lion, and who ſhall ſtirre him up,</hi> Numbers 24.5, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who then can be meant, but theſe that ſhall riſe up for the Lord againſt evil doers, and ſtand up againſt the workers of iniquity,</hi> Pſ. 94.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in whoſe mouths ſhall be the praiſes of the Lord, and a two edged ſword in their hand, To execute vengeance upon the Heathen, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the people, and to have that honour to binde their Kings with chains, and their Nobles with fetters of Iron,</hi> Pſ. 149.6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Theſe fore-cited texts in the general, with many more the like are properly applicable to the Iſraelites the natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> at their return and reſtoration into their own land, the land of Canaan, as is evident to any rational man, (that carries not both his eyes in his pocket) that ſhall but conſult theſe texts particularly and impartially, not being preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced by any uncouth and abſurd ſenſes put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by the traditions of men; for when the text in <hi>Ier.</hi> 31:31: ſhall ſay thus: <hi>Behold the dayes come, ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and with the houſe of Juda, not according to the covenant
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170139:48"/>that I made with their fathers, in the day that I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Covenant is again repeated long after in the ſame words to the ſame people, <hi>Heb:</hi> 8: beſides the place in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> expreſſeth Gods further promiſe to them; (namely) That after thoſe dayes he would put his law in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and write it in their hearts, and that all of them ſhould know the Lord, and their iniquities ſhould then be forgiven them, <hi>verſe</hi> 33, 34: and in <hi>Ierem:</hi> 32:40, 41, 42. the ſame Covenant is again repeated thus: That the Lord would make an everlaſting covenant with them, that he will not turn away from them to do them good, but would put his fear in their hearts, that they ſhould not depart from him, yea he would rejoyce over them to do them good, and would plant them in that land (the land of Canaan) aſſuredly, with his whole heart, and with his whole ſoul, and like as he had brought all this great evil upon this people, ſo he would bring upon them all the good that he promiſed them, and in <hi>verſe</hi> 37, 39. it is ſaid, That God would gather them out of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, whither he had driven them in his anger, and in his fury and in great wrath, and would bring them again in that place (the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan) and would cauſe them to dwell ſafely, and would give them one heart, and one way, that they ſhould fear him for ever, for the good of them and their children after them.</p>
            <p>Which plainly ſets forth the converſion of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170139:48"/>the Jews to the true fear of God, and never more to depart from him, and their being ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of all Countreys into their own land again, to be there ſafely planted aſſuredly, both they and their children after them, to fear the Lord for ever, which was never yet perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to this people.</p>
            <p>It cannot be meant that this Covenant is promiſed to be made with any Gentile belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or Churches already converted, whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were never led by the hand out of Egypt, nor planted in the land of Canaan, to be there again re-planted, much leſs can it be meant of every Gentile Church or Congregation of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed believers, as it is uſually expounded and applied by the ſeveral Paſtors and Miniſters to their reſpective Congregations; but they may as ſoon make me believe, that all they ſay is truth, as to believe this expoſition of theirs; or that this is not meant of Iſrael and Juda, the very natural ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> or that it doth not mean the general converſion and gathering of that people into their own land again; out of which they have been driven, even the natural Iſraelites, whoſe converſion Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively aſſerts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. by the name of Iſrael, the natural branches, and his kinſmen accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, affirming them to be holy, and beloved for their fathers ſake, even when they were broken off, and in the ſtate of unbelief, (wherein they yet remain unto this day) term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtian Romans (though their faith was then famous throughout the whole world) Gentiles; and in compariſon of them but wild
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170139:49"/>branches cut out of the wilde Olave-tree, and then after many hints of their coverſion, of their being received and graffed in again, at laſt affirms, that all (or the whole houſe of) Iſrael ſhal be ſaved, and proves it by that which is written in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.20. (which is) That the Redeemer ſhall come to Sion, and to them which turn from tranſgreſſion, in <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſaith the Lord As for me this is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord, my ſpirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, ſaith the Lord, from henceforth, and for ever.</p>
            <p>Hence it is evident, by Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the great deliverance, bleſſing, and mercy intended and meant in this text, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongeth unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> or natural children of Iſrael, whence it will follow, That the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, permanent glory, ſecurity and peace, propheſied and ſpoken of in the chapter imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately following appertains to them alſo, none whereof being fulfilled when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote that Epiſtle, nor at any time ſince, it is all yet to be fulfilled to them: And therefore whoſoever expounds this Scripture otherwiſe, thwarts Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to the deceiving both of themſelves and others, which is much and often done by ſuch as turn the true and plain ſenſe of this and other Scriptures into myſtical or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorical meanings, the meer inventions of mens brains, whereby many excellent paſſages of Scripture, yea in effect the whole Scripture
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170139:49"/>hath been and is perverted, and made (not help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful but) hurtful to many, which if rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood would be of excellent uſe and benefit to all men; but by ſuch and the like miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, and blind ſenſes put upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures by our blinde guides, and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>And have we not ſeen, Curſe ye Meroz diſplayed, nor heard them curſed bitterly, who came not out to help the Lord, nor yet known many honeſt and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere hearts extreamly cheated on all ſides, and by none more then by ſuch charms and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who though they knew little of the right application of that text, yet, it bearing a ſound for their purpoſe, it was made uſe of by them meerly upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign &amp; intereſt; for no ſooner did they perceive the waters begin to run beſides their Mill,</hi> (i.e. <hi>their ambitions, covetous, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering ends were not ſerved) but they turned cat in pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; curſed as faſt the contrary way; &amp; this at pleaſure upon occaſion can they do</hi> (viz.) <hi>bleſs &amp; curſe, curſe and bleſs, one &amp; the ſame perſon, one and the ſame cauſe, one and the ſame opinion, with one and the ſame mouth, and poſſible from one &amp; the ſame text.</hi>
               </note> corrupt intereſſed men, as it may ſeem, the honeſt zeal and good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe men (I ſpeak as charity bindes me) hath been ſo much miſled as to conceive themſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, to make this raſh and un-adviſed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous both to themſelves and the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But if inſtead thereof they had imployed all the power &amp; intereſt they had in a lawful
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170139:50"/>way upon a civil account to have procured for the honeſt and good people of the Nations, the performance of ſuch honeſt and righteous things, as of right do belong unto them, and are but the juſt return of all the blood &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure laid out and ſpent by them, for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or rather for the redemption of them, and which have been ſo much and ſo often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them, and that upon moſt-ſolemn &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred appeals to heaven, (and yet hitherto moſt unjuſtly
<note n="*" place="margin">But we be to them and him, by whom theſe offences come.</note> deteined from them) I conceive they had been far leſs (if at all) blama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then in that which they have attempted: For can they think it juſt for them to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer over their fellows and brethren, meerly by a ſuppoſed divine authority from Scripture, and may not any other upon the ſame account, by a contrary expoſition put upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture challenge the like ſuperiority over them? and muſt not we then needs fight it out, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conclude the ſtrongeſt to have expounded trueſt; for the weakeſt muſt to the wall, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps into ſome caſtle, or priſon, or into the bottome of ſome dungeon, as erroneous, or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical perſons, whilſt all ſuch as have but the power over caſtles and priſons are alwayes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox all the world over, and who may ſay to the contrary?</p>
            <p>Or can they think it reaſonable or feaſable for them to ſet up that Kingdome of Chriſt, to prevent and ſave him the labour of coming, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170139:50"/>ſo to rob him of the glory of doing it himſelf, by the mighty power of his own arm, without the arm of fleſh, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 63.1, to 7: whereby he will exalt his great name and glory to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, more then by any of his former archieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The bringing the children of Iſrael thorow the red Sea, out of the hands of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> was indeed a very wonderful and glorious work, whereby God made his Name great in all the earth, yet this his deliverance and reſtoring of them (yet to come) and his ſetting up of his Kingdome will ſo far and ſo much exceed that, that it will ſwallow it up, and cauſe it to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as the light of a candle will do at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Sun, and ſo far bury it in oblivion, that it ſhall never more be remembred for ever, <hi>Jer.:</hi> 23 from 3: to 9.</p>
            <p>This whole life is the time for the Saints and righteous to ſuffer in, for, and in hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and reſt in that Kingdome, with Chriſt at his coming, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1:4, to 9: but theſe men would fain be reaping before harveſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time of ſowing is ended; and be reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that Kingdome before the bleſſed Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and Apoſtles, who yet ſleep in the duſt, and who are to be the prime heirs and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours with Chriſt of that Kingdome, <hi>Matth</hi> 8:11: <hi>Luke</hi> 22:30: yea, and without, and before Chriſt there raigns himſelf, and before that Kingdome, or the time of ſetting it up be come, which may not be.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170139:51"/>
            <p>But the authority aſſumed and now attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by theſe men, ſeems (at leaſt to me) to be much like to that which is exerciſed by his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe the Pope, as Chriſts Vice-gerent upon earth, over all both perſons and cauſes, for which he pretends divine authority, and that from Scripture alſo; for from <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.13. which ſayes (thus) <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lion and Adder, the young Lion and Dragon thou ſhalt tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By pretence of divine authority from this Scripture, he moſt preſumptuouſly tramples under foot all civil Magiſtracy, and ſets his feet upon the necks of Emperours. Like as I my ſelf once heard <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45.16. expounded from a Pulpit in <hi>Pauls:</hi> the Text runs thus; <hi>Inſtead of thy Fathers ſhall thy children be, whom thou ſhalt make Princes thorow all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Fathers (ſaid he) are meant the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and Apoſtles; and by Children are meant the Lords Biſhops, who are their ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>Hence this learned Preacher, in further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of this his Text, with great confidence aſſerted the principality of Biſhops, and their ſuperiority over other Miniſters to be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right.</p>
            <p>And there's no doubt, but theſe (called fifth Monarchy-men) may prove their dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all others to be of Divine right as well as this. Nay, who can doubt, but that Presbyters, Independents, Separatiſts, Anabaptiſts, yea and Mahometan Prieſts alſo can prove their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170139:51"/>authorities to be of divine right, as well as either of the former, and that from Scripture too; and if they can not, they are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſuch offices of dignity, and ſuch places of profit, as to be Maſters and Heads of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, &amp;c. and if the Revenues of the beſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks were alſo added thereto, there's no doubt but that theſe would eaſily ſwallow it up, without making any bones thereat, the name being onely changed.</p>
            <p>Nay, have we not had ſome, who lately ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on horſ-back into <hi>Briſtol,</hi> received ſuch honour, acclamations, and attributes, as were given to Chriſt when he rode into Jeruſalem: and no doubt but all this was done by ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority drawn from the Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. where the manner of Chriſts ſo riding into Jeruſalem is recited.</p>
            <p>And why might not the horſe have run and bruiſed the riders foot againſt a wall by divine authority likewiſe from that Scripture, which recites how that <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe dealt ſo, by that falſe prophet, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22 25.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall, at preſent, forbear to trace this divine Goddeſs and great Idol any further, but ſhall now leave her to the view of all men, as ſhe is ſet forth in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. like a Queen ſitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Throne, moſt ſumptuouſly arraied in purple and ſcarlet, and gilded with gold, and precious ſtones, and pearls, having a cup in her hand full of abominations and filthineſs of her fornication; upon whom the more I look, the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170139:52"/>more I wonder, even with greateſt admiration, when I conſider how ſuch a counterfeit painted ſtrumpet as this, hath ſo much, ſo long, and ſo univerſally beguiled (in effect) the whole world, and intoxicated many ſuch men, as are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt exquiſite, wiſe and exact in far ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler matters.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now conclude, removing onely a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which from this Diſcourſe may ariſe in ſome honeſt hearts to this effect:</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Since there is no name given under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whereby men can be ſaved, but by the name of Ieſus Chriſt, and none can be ſaved by that name but ſuch as truly believe therein; and none can have a ſufficient ground for true and Chriſtian faith, but by a true Miniſtry, evidencing the truth and divine authority of their doctrine, by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the Spirit, and power of God. And if the caſe be ſo, as by this Diſcourſe it ſeems to be; In what condition are all ſuch, who never enjoyed ſuch a Miniſtry? is not their caſe neceſſarily dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay no; for although it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That none are ſaved but by Chriſt, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny millions of thouſands may be and are ſaved, and that by Chriſt, who never enjoyed any ſuch Miniſtry, never believed in Chriſt, nor heard of him; for what elſe think we, ſhould become of all infants ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> who died in their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, whoſe ſalvation (at leaſt) their freedome from condemnation, cannot (upon any good ground) be doubted of: for they have ſuffered
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170139:52"/>death, the natural effect of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from which at the reſurrection they ſhall be redeemed and diſcharged by Chriſt, for what or for whoſe ſin can they then be condemned at the day of Judgement, ſince they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted none themſelves, and ſhall have already ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered death for <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and from which they ſhall then be acquitted by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And their ſalvation (as I conceive) is as little to be doubted of, becauſe that condition or ſort of mankinde, which Chriſt himſelf did put as a preſident and example for his Diſciples to conform themſelves to, for to become inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the Kingdome of heaven, muſt needs be inheritours of the Kingdome of heaven, but ſuch are little children: and Chriſt affirmed, that of ſuch is the Kingdom of heaven, and who then hath need or reaſon to doubt thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſame may be deemed the caſe of all born Ideots living and dying ſo.</p>
            <p>And what may be thought of all the Heathen nations &amp; people in the world (ſince <hi>Adam</hi>) that have lived to years of diſcretion, can any man reaſonably think that God hath left all theſe quite deſtitute of all means of ſalvation, and of acceptance with him? did God afford them, or any of them ſuch an ample excuſe at the day of judgement, as they might then have upon that account? No ſurely, for then all mens mouths will be ſtopped, and no ſuch reaſonable and juſt excuſe ſhall be found in the mouth of any.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170139:53"/>
            <p>What meaneth Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, (in <hi>Act.</hi> 17.25, 26, 27.) <hi>That God had made of one blood all Nations to dwell on the face of the earth, giving to all life, breath, and all things (as rain from heaven, and fruitful ſeaſons, filling their hearts with food and gladneſs,</hi> chap: 14:17:) and to what end did God all this, but that they might ſeek him, and haply find him, not being far from any of them, giving them (by theſe daily bleſſings) opportunity at leaſt to know, conſider, and thankfully to acknowledge ſome divine goodneſs (be it under what name or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever) to be the authour and bountiful beſtower of theſe daily mercies, whereby as God leaves not himſelf without witneſs, ſo he leaves all without excuſe or ability to plead that they were deſtitute of all means to obtain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, to their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Again, what means the giving of talents; to ſome more, to ſome leſs, or fewer, but to all ſome; one at leaſt, to know good and evil; ſo far as to know when another wrongs him; in like proportion muſt he know when he wrongs another; and that as he would not have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrong him in the leaſt, ſo ſhould not he do the leaſt wrong to any other; but to do as he would be done unto, according to the Golden Rule, or Law written in every mans heart. What elſe meaneth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2:26, 27. <hi>If the uncircumciſion keeps the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Law, ſhall not his uncircumciſion be counted for circumciſion, and ſhall not the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion which is by nature, if it fulfill the law,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170139:53"/>judge thee, who by the letter and circumciſion doſt tranſgreſs the Law.</hi> See further the 11, 12, 13, 14, 15 verſes of the ſame Chapter, wherein it is ſaid thus; <hi>When the Gentiles which have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, having not the law, are a law unto themſelves, which ſhews the work of the law written in their hearts, their conſciences alſo bearing witneſs, and their thoughts in the mean while accuſing or elſe excuſing one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What may we think of <hi>Iob,</hi> being an upright and juſt man that feared God, and eſchewed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil? what can be thought of <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad, Zoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Eliphaz,</hi> and <hi>Elihu,</hi> but that they were ſober, honeſt, wiſe, and juſt men fearing God, although they were miſtaken (as who might not) in <hi>Iobs</hi> particular and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe.</p>
            <p>And what meaneth the ſtory of <hi>Cornelius, Act:</hi> 10: being an uncircumciſed Gentile deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the knowledge of Chriſt, yet had acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance with God, and his prayers heard not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. And what think you of <hi>Peters</hi> Proclamation thereupon, ſaying; Of a truth I perceive, that God is no reſpecter of perſons, but in every Nation, he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted with him.</p>
            <p>Hence I conceive, (without offence to any otherwiſe minded) may be concluded;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That all thoſe who never enjoyed true Miniſtry of the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſhall
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170139:54"/>never be judged for not believing, or not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel of Chriſt; but ſhall be judged either as in ſincerity they have indeavoured to obſerve the good, and eſchew the evil known to them; or have wilfully ſwerved from it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance and amendment; for God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts men according to that they have, and not according to that they have not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>And to whom much is given, of him only much ſhall be required: and little of him to whom little is given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That God never concluded any Nation or perſon ſo to condemnation, as not to afford them and him ſufficient means within his reach and power to eſcape the ſame, and to procure acceptance with him.</p>
            <p>Theſe J deem (with ſubmiſſion to better Judgements) may as ſafely and truly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, as to affirm, That God is moſt juſt, good, and merciful, That his mercy is extended over all the works of his hands, who hateth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he hath made, but filleth all things with his goodneſs, and heareth the young Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens that cry to him for meat, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.27, 28. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145.16, 17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 147.9.</p>
            <p>Accurſed then are the tongues and pens of ſuch evil ſervants, that render this indulgent, bountiful, and good Maſter to be hard and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteer, to reap where he did not ſowe, and to propoſe grace and mercy to far the greateſt part of the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> when
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170139:54"/>he never intended it to any of them; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe had inevitably, abſolutely and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally concluded them to exquiſite and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs miſery, of his meer will and power, long before they were born, and that without reſpect to any ſinful or evil action of theirs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 27.5.</hi>
               </bibl> Open rebuke is better then ſecret love.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 12.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Who ſo loveth inſtruction, loveth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but he that hateth reproof is bruitiſh.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 28 16.</hi>
               </bibl> The Prince that wanteth underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is alſo a great oppreſſour, but he that hateth covetouſneſs, ſhall prolong his dayes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 17:</hi>
               </bibl> A man that doth violence to the blood of any perſon ſhall flee to the pit, let no man ſtay him.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 29.1.</hi>
               </bibl> He that being often reproved, hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 27.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Faithful are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitful.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:170139:55"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>MR. John Brayne, <hi>a learned man, in his Book intituled</hi> (The unknown Being) <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> 1654. <hi>in</hi> page 3. <hi>telleth us, as a matter of exceeding great note and concernment to all men, which is the groſs corruptings of the Word of God, in the falſe tranſlating of it, the Tranſlators put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down in an hundred places neer, life for ſoul, rendring</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>life, and ſometimes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſoul, which ought not to be, the word and ſenſe is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, and falſe doctrine taught to the people: wherefore in eſpecial there is an extream neceſſity of another Tranſlation to be publiſhed, and this called in: The Old Teſtament in this particular is better tranſlated then the New, though ſome ſuch in the Old, as that the mind of God is no way expreſſed, but clean contrary things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in</hi> page 11. <hi>he further telleth us,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That its no wonder</hi> Auſtine <hi>and others run to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy (having loſt the knowledge of the Spirit, which was immortal) to prove the ſoul immortal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scripture; upon which Philoſophical hinges the Divinity of the now times are hanged, in which, Untruths, Errours, and Deceits are told the people, to the overthrow of hope, and ſhaking of
<pb facs="tcp:170139:55"/>faith in men, and deſtruction of the truth;</hi> And in this follow not the Lords Spirit, but their own, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi>After my ſetting down this learned Authors judgement (concurring with the reſt of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors formerly cited) concerning the erroneous Tranſlations of Scripture, there came to my hand another ſmall Treatiſe of his</hi> (<hi>intituled</hi> Heavens witneſs to the worſhip and worſhippers on earth) <hi>wherein he not onely confirmes what in this Diſcourſe is aſſerted for the neceſſity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and powerful evidence, to atteſt the truth of doctrine, Believers, and Churches of the Goſpel; but alſo ſhews how God by ſome ſuch divine evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence gave witneſs to true worſhip, both before the law, in time of the law, and to the worſhip of the Goſpel from Chriſt to the Apoſtaſie,</hi> Anno 406.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with abundant Teſtimonies of Scripture, proving that the Truth and the true Church was not, nor when reſtored, ſhall not be without the ſame; with which (as at firſt) God again will reſtore the Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170139:56"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN page 3. line 16. for <hi>inceſtur</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremie,</hi> read, <hi>mice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Irency.</hi> pag. 6. lin. 17. for <hi>pareas minori,</hi> read <hi>pareas inſane minori.</hi> l. 21. r. <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> p. 7. l. 7. r. allowable. l. 16. r. <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> and there and elſewhere for <hi>Sextus,</hi> r. <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> p. 12. l. 21. f. untelligable, r. unintelligable. p. 14. l. 1. r. <hi>Breſcia.</hi> p. 20. l. 7. r. <hi>in ore gladii Cruentandi.</hi> p. 23. l. 25. r. <hi>Anthographs.</hi> p. 27. l. 24. r. of the Trinity. p. 51. l. ult. r. veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. p. 55. l. ult. r. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7, 12. p. 72. l. 3. f. He that hath, r. He that believeth hath. p. 81. l. 9. f. on, r. by. &amp; l. 10. f. by, r. on.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
